<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The acquital or purgation of the moost catholyke Christen Prince, Edwarde the .VI. Kyng of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande &amp;c. and of the Churche of Englande refourmed and gouerned under hym, agaynst al suche as blasphemously and traitorously infame hym or the sayd Church, of heresie or sedicion.</title>
            <author>Old, John, fl. 1545-1555.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1555</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18797</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101902</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837705</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837705</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2045</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08471)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2045)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1029:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The acquital or purgation of the moost catholyke Christen Prince, Edwarde the .VI. Kyng of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande &amp;c. and of the Churche of Englande refourmed and gouerned under hym, agaynst al suche as blasphemously and traitorously infame hym or the sayd Church, of heresie or sedicion.</title>
                  <author>Old, John, fl. 1545-1555.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By E. van der Erve,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Emprinted at Vvaterford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>the 7. day of Nouembre. 1555]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Old.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from colophon; printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The imprint is generally considered fictitious; Plomer suggests Emden as actual place of publication.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F.</note>
                  <note>Title page marked and stained; leaf E1 cropped. Signatures E-F from Folger Shakespeare Library copy spliced at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Edward --  VI, --  King of England, 1537-1553 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2045:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2045:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The acquital or pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gation of the mooſt catholyke Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten Prince, <hi>EDwarde</hi> the
<hi>.VI.</hi> Kyng of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande &amp;c. and of the Churche of Englande refourmed and gouerned vnder hym, agaynſt al ſuche as blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly and traitorouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infame hym or the ſayd Church, of hereſie or ſedicion.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <hi>They are gone to Baal Peor, and runne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye from the Lorde to that shamefull Idole, and are become as abominable as theyr louers. Ephraim fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth lyke a birde, ſo shall theyr glorye alſo. </hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Oſe.</hi> 9.</bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:2045:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2045:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the nobilitie and to the reſte of the charitable chriſten laytie of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, Iohn Olde wiſheth grace and mercy from god the father, and from Ieſus Chriſt the common and only ſaueour of the worlde, with the gifte of perfite faithe &amp; ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt repentaunce.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuche as the preachers in Englande now promoted and ſet vp in throne by the Quenes highneſſe, aſwell at Paules croſſe as commonly in open pulpittes (in place of Chriſtes ſyncere goſpel) ſpewe out with ſcol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, roaring, and railing, the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable poiſon of Antichriſts tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciones, as holſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> medicine for the ſoul: infamyng therwith the order, forme, and vſe of preaching, prayer, &amp; admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtracion of the holy ſacramentes, ſet furthe and exerciced by common autoritie in the churche of Englande refourmed vnder the gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the moſt chriſten King and maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Chryſtes catholyke faythe, King Edwarde the .vi. and moſt vilie ſlaundering his famous father King Henry the .viii. for banyſhing the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent

<pb facs="tcp:2045:3"/>vſurped power and ſupremacie of the Romyſhe auncient Antichriſt, for being dyuorced from his brothers knowne wyfe, and for takyng iuſtly vpon him the title &amp; eſtate of ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy incident and aperteynyng (by the vndoubted ordinaunce of God) to his Regal office &amp; emperiall crowne: So that euery indifferent harte enlu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myned eyther with the ſpirite of God by the inſtruction of his holy worde and goſpel, or with any common vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of natural loue and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile duetie of obedience to his ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayne liege lordes, Goddes lieutena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untes vnder Chriſt vpon earthe, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueth thoſe falſe prophetes and prowde pau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched praters to be therin not only horrible blaſphemers of the holy gooſt, enemies of chriſtes croſſe, tearours of his ſeameles coate, defy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of his bleſſed ordinaunces, comp trollers of his holy Apoſtles and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matyue true catholike churche, and moſte bloody furious rauening wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes among his ſely ſhepe, but alſo moſt harde harted heretikes, moſte haynous traitours againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crowne and their countrey, moſt ſedicious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belles againſt the vnitie of peace and
<pb facs="tcp:2045:3"/>tranquillitie of the realme, moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured peſtilent papiſtes, and moſt wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uering wethercockes: like as in their further frutes they are notoryouſly knowne to be holowe harted hoore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, moſt ſawcye ſhameleſſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites, the manciples of myſchief, and very ſlaues of Satan, and (if they repent not the more ſpedily) the moſt fitte fyre brandes of the perpetual fla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myng fornace of hell. Albeit no fewe in Englande haue moſt faithfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted the babling blaſphemye &amp; falſe forged fables of the mytred maſkers and ſhauen ſwarme of ſhameles ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites, not only in ſuffring ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, tolde, pouertie, vnquietneſſe, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynfull pryſone, but alſo in pacient be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aring of the croſſe of fyre, galowes &amp; ſweorde euen vnto the deathe, to the comforte and ſtreynghtenyng of Chriſtes weake flocke, to the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng of many y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were wofully wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in popiſhe errours, and to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of the luſty railing reprobates them ſelues and all their trayne: Yet conſidering it the bounden duetie of euery true harted ſubiecte to defend with all his poſſible power, the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie and truthe of his natural ſoue
<pb facs="tcp:2045:4"/>rayne againſt the traitorous talke &amp; enuious iniurie of railing reporters, and ſpecially in Chriſtes cauſe (whoſe miniſters and officers all Princes &amp; Kinges ar) whoſe worde and lawe al chryſtianes are moſt ſtraytly dette bounden not only to embrace, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> belefe of the harre, but alſo to confeſſe it openly with mouthe a mydde mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the aduouterous ſynfull generacion of rule and power of this worlde, and ſpirituall wyckedneſſe in heauenly thinges: I haue thought it no leſſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my duetie, being a naturall engliſhe man, and ſworne to the loyaltie and obedyence of thoſe worthy famous chriſten kinges againſt the ſodomiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Syre of Rome, and all forayn po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers (as all thoſe periured wether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rockes the ſhauen ſorcerers were) to anſwerre the forſworne ſwarme and rable of railing rutterkines, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe and purgacion of chriſtes catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like flocke,
<note place="margin">Prieſtes the locu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lande.</note> called the goſpellers chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, ſpecially reſpecting the chriſten euangelical churche of Englande re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed and gouerned by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, rule, and practice of Chriſtes moſt holy ſacred euangelical law, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our forſaide moſt chriſten catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke
<pb facs="tcp:2045:4"/>ſouerayne, King Edwarde the vi. who, according to the principall poynt of his regal office and charge (and according to the foteſteppes and examples of Moſes, Ioſua, Dauid, Salomö, Ezechias, Ioſias, Ioſaphat and other moſt godly gouernours &amp; kinges, whiche haue their perpetuall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendacion in the regeſtre of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des voke for their hartie diligence &amp; trauailes in the aduaunceing of hys pure religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) ſought chiefly the glorie of God, the honour of chriſt crucified, his owne edifyeng and diſcharge of conſcience, and the inſtruction &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his ſubiectes in the true knowlage, faythe, feare and loue of God and his glorious goſpel, and to buylde the churche of Englande (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted of God to his Regall charge) only vpon the foundacion of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes and apoſtles, and to ſcowre the ſame from the curſed cuſtomes, and traunting tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es of Satans ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſinagoge. Albeit I could make a docket of remembraunce, how you of the nobilitie (that were put in autori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and truſt vnder the king) might &amp; ought haue anſwered and vſed thoſe lecherous lieng locuſtes, according to
<pb facs="tcp:2045:5"/>the ordre of iuſtice, bi examples bothe of diuine and prophane hiſtories, and by the ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cial godly lauful law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the realme, for their traitorous ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring &amp; railing vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, their owne naturall liege lorde, for their recaryeng of their infernall father the abiured antichriſt of Rome in to Englande agayn, for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing of forayn powers in to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, for their falſe foxelye forgeing of fables (among the buſye headed vulgare commones) againſte theyr natural nobilitie, &amp; for theyr others to deueliſhe demerites beſydes: yet now ſeing you haue allready runne to farre, againſt your owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, ſo that it ſemeth almoſt to late for any admonicion or reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſynke in to your hartes, being afrayde of euerye barking blaſte of Antichriſtes bawdye beagles, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentig your ſelues to be ledde (like an oxe) by horne and eare, as it pleaſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to appoynt, til they haue brought you to blocklaye faire in to the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter houſe, as they haue done a greate ſorte of your beſt fedde felowes, I ſhal ſpare my pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, &amp; with my conti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nual prayers for your preſeruacion
<pb facs="tcp:2045:5"/>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr clouthes, leaue you to God &amp; your ſelues. In the meane while, ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; oportunitie, I ſhal ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe thoſe wicked wormes a reaſonable anſwer, leaſte in kepyng ſilence and wynkyng at their licencious libertie &amp; wickedneſſe, we ſeme to be afrayde of theyr obiectiones, &amp; ſo make folkes beleue, they were true, or to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage that the faultes, wherof they ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefulli ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre vs, were in vs in dede. The ſcripture alſo by the eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſtes and apoſtles commaundeth and bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs to defende the truthe, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute lyes, to beare recorde vnto the truthe, and to acquyte the faythfull chriſtianes in theyr innocencye and ryght. But what can a man doo in ſo furyons a rageing rable of aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, and Iniuryous entreatyng of men? Or how ſhold a man begynne to defende the churche, ſeyng ſuch a ſorte of cruell and maddebrayned e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies obiecte ſo many and ſo hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous crymes agaynſt vs, and dyng on as it were wyth quartre ſtrokes on euery ſyde? Whan. S. Paule the preacher of the Gentyles and moſte choſen veſſell of Chryſt was accuſed him ſelfe of the Iewes, in a ſingular
<pb facs="tcp:2045:6"/>good cauſe, euen the cauſe of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, furſt before Antonius Felix, and efteſones before Portius Feſtus lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenauntes of Iewrye, of many ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and was more than ouerlayde wyth the power, eloquence, autoritie, and reputacion of hys aduerſaries, &amp; could obteyne nother place nor ſpace, to anſwere vnto euery point through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he thought he ſhould defende hym ſelfe and hys cauſe wel ynough, yf he myght ſhewe by ſome euident &amp; moſt playne homely ſhorte reaſons, that he neuer taught contrarye to the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, nor agaynſt the hope of Iſrael, but that he was iniuriouſly enuyed &amp; preſſed of hys enemyes for conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye preachyng and defendyng of the hope of the Reſurrection, whych the Iſraelites holde.</p>
            <p>And now folowyng his moſte godly and ſingular good exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple (and vſyng the helpe, ordre, and almoſte the very wordes of a certayn notable profou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de learned Paſtour, who hath done the ſame in latine, in defence and purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the chriſten goſpellike flocke &amp; churche committed to hys ſpiritual charge) ſeyng I am barred out of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and tyme (as an abiecte out of my
<pb facs="tcp:2045:6"/>natural countrey) ſo that I can not poſſibly anſwere to all theyr odious obiections in ordre &amp; one by one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly by them ſelues, I ſhal yet by the helpe of God, do myn endeauour to declare and ſet before all mennes eyes (by the waye of tranſlation, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther myne owne edicion) that whyche is moſte chief and generall mater in thys cauſe, wyth the moſte cleare and playne argumentes that I can: that is to wete, that the Churche of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande refourmed and gouerned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Kyng Edwarde the .vi. was no heretical, ſchiſmatical, nor ſedicious Church: and that all other Churches embraceyng the Goſpel in aſſembla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wyſe, are no heretical nor ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tical Churches, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vndenyable chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che of Ieſus Chriſt bothe true, fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and catholike. Wherfore I beſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che you ryght honourable lordes, ryght worſhipfull gentilmen, and the reſt of my charytable chryſten coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen, for the loue and loyaltye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you bare and owed to your moſt chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten and moſte louyng ſouerayne lie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge lorde and maiſter Kyng Edwarde the .vi. reade or heare thys ſimple ſhorte treatyſe paciently and gentlye,
<pb facs="tcp:2045:7"/>inaſmuche as I ſhal do my diligence as euidentlye and in as fewe wordes as I poſſibly can, to ſpeake not of all thynges, that myght be alleged in thys behalfe, but ſuche reaſons onely, as chiefly and principally concerne thys preſent cauſe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>The fyrſt Chaptre.</head>
            <p>FYrſt where Chriſt our Lorde ſayeth, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llerschur
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e recea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ole Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> my ſhepe heare my voyce: the churche of Chriſte (whyche to be knowne from the churche of Papiſtes, is cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led the goſpellers church, as the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of Englande in Kyng Edwardes tyme was) dothe acknowlege and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the Canonical bokes bothe of the olde Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and newe, as thoſe that were proclaymed and ſpoken out of Boddes owne mouthe. Ther is none of them, that it denyeth or refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, but receaueth and reteyneth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al holly and perfytly. Nother doth it capciouſly reaſon, about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> receauyng of thoſe bokes, who hath receaued them, or who hath refuſed them: nor whether is of greater force, the auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of the churche receauyng the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures,
<pb facs="tcp:2045:7"/>or of the ſcriptures them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues receaued. For albeit we read that S. Auſten wrote thus: <hi>Non crederem Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gelio, niſi eccleſiae catholicae autoritas me co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moue ret.</hi> I wold geue no crede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (ſayth he) vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell, if the autorytye of the catholike churche dyd not inoue me: yet Berſon the chauncellour of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, <note place="margin">Gerſon.</note> a ryght excellent famous man in hys tyme, dothe in hys ſeconde boke
<hi>De vita ſpirituali</hi> like a diſcrete profou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de learned clerke, ſaye: S. Auſten in that place, taketh the churche for the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mityue congregacion of thoſe fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men, that harde and ſawe Chriſt, &amp; were his recorde bearours. For whan, ther crepte out dyuerſe ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Boſpelles in the churche, while the apoſtles &amp; diſciples of Chriſt were yet lyuing, they that hade ſene Chriſt him ſelfe, &amp; hade harde hys apoſtles, could teſtifye whych were ryght and true, and whych were not. Ireneus alſo in the .xi. chapter of his
.3. boke <hi>Contra haereſes,</hi> ſheweth by many many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt proues, that ther ought to be but only <hi>4.</hi> goſpelles, and yet he maketh no mencion of the churche, that ther ought to be but only <hi>4.</hi> goſpelles, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the churche hathe receaued no
<pb facs="tcp:2045:8"/>moo but only <hi>4.</hi> but bycauſe the Lord hath ſo appointed. For ther was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer man that in any Conuocacion or Synode aſſembled al for that purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe from the begynnyng, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed the Canonical bokes of the ſcriptures, or decreed which were canonical, which were not, but the thurche as it recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them of the writours, &amp; autours the holy Prophetes and Apeſtles the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo dyd it delyuer them (as it were by hande) vnto her poſteritie. It was late ere it bego<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to be decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in counſailes vpon canonical and not canonical bokes of ſcripture: not that ther was no diuerſitye of them before that tyme, or that the bokes of holy ſcripture had none autoritye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that tyme (as they hade and muſt haue dyuine autoritye in dede, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ther hade neuer ben counſayl holden) but that the holy men of God were diſpoſed to ſhewe their iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t alſo, agaynſt ſuche as bare to vnfren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a minde agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> canonical bokes of ſcripture. And we confeſſe al, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche is buylded and ſet vpon the foundacion of the Prophetes and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles: ſo if the doctrine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles and prophetes be the foundaceon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2045:8"/>churche, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it foloweth of neceſſytye, that the autoritye of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine muſt nedes be of greater force and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, than the autoritie of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. We therfore in Englande dyd re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaue, as the Goſpellers church elles where doth ſtil receaue al and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Canonical bokes both of the olde Teſtament and newe, and namelye thoſe that the Greke wrytours <hi>Melito, Origene,</hi> and <hi>Euſebius Caeſarienſis,</hi> and of the Latines <hi>Cipriane</hi> and <hi>Ierome</hi> haue affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by theyr owne ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de wrytynges, to be taken and reputed of the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent fathers, yea euen from the begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng, for the vndoubted true Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical ſcriptures.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The ſeconde Chapter.</head>
            <p>AS touching the truthe and perfyte integritye of theſe bokes, <note place="margin">Of the truth and perfection of the canen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> we doubt nothyng therof at al: &amp; in ſuch places as be doubtful &amp; hard to vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtand, we teache men to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe vnto the oryginall fountaynes wherout they were tranſlated. S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten <hi>contra Adimantum</hi> the
<hi>3.</hi> chap. ſaithe: <hi>Si admittamus haereticis, quod cauſſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, libros
<pb facs="tcp:2045:9"/>ſacros eſſe corruptos, nullus erit contentionum fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi> That is: yf we graunt vnto the he retikes (as they fynde fault) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of holy ſcripture are corrupt, ther wylbe none ende of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tencion. And in the, <hi>2.</hi> chap. of hys .xi. boke <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Fau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtum Manichaeum,</hi> he ſayeth: <hi>Si de fide ex emplarium quaeſtio verteretur, ſicut &amp; in nonnullis quae paucae ſunt &amp; ſacrarum li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terarum ſtudioſis notiſsimae ſententiarum varietates, vel ex aliarum regionu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> codi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibus vnde ipſa doctrina co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meauit noſtra dubitatio dijudicaretur: vel ſi ibi quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> co dices variare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, plures paucioribus, aut ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tustiores recentioribus praeferrentur. Et ſi adhuc incerta eſſet varietas, praecedens lingua, vnde illud interpretatum eſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuleretur.</hi> Yf queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be moued, concernyng the credence to be geuen vnto the copyes of the bokes of holye ſcriptures, as it chaunceth in ſome diuerſities of ſentences, whyche are but a fewe, and knowen (at the fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers endes) to them that be ſtudentes of holy ſcriptures, eyther our doubt muſte be reſolued by the textes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treyes whence that doctrine came, or elles yf the textes themſelues dyd varye in that behalfe, the greater
<pb facs="tcp:2045:9"/>nombre ſhould be preferred before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fewer, or the auncienter before the yonger. And in caſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuerſitye were yet ſtill vncertayn, it ſhould be tryed bi the former tongue wherout it was interpreted or tranſlated. For the ſame Auſten rehearceth in an other place &amp; it is alleged in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> decrees <hi>Diſt. 9 vt veteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> libroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fides de Hebraeis voluminibus examina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da eſt, ita nouorum veritas Graeci ſera monis normam deſiderat</hi> That is: like as the truthe of the bokes of the olde teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is to be tryed by the Hebrue tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ſo muſt the bokes of the newe be ruled by the truthe of the greke tong. And agayn in the .xi. chaptre of hys ſeconde boke <hi>De doctrina Chriſtiana,</hi> he ſaythe: <hi>Latini homines &amp; duabus alijs ad ſcripturarum diuinarum cognitionem opus habent, Hebraea ſcilicet &amp; Graeca, vt ad exemplaria praecedentia recurratur, ſi qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dubitationem attulerit latinorum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretum infinita varietas.</hi> Latine men (ſayeth he) had nede of two other to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues alſo to the perfyte knowlege of holy ſcripture, that is to ſaye, the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue and Greke, that they maye haue recourſe vnto the original copyes, in caſe the infinite diuerſytye of latine interpretours haue cauſed any doubt
<pb facs="tcp:2045:10"/>Thus muche ſaithe Auſten, whythe hathe taught vs to be more fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto the ſondry tranſlaciones of the Bible, and to iudge more purely of the authentike boke being written in bys owne language, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes wonted maner is, whych takyng vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue the holy gooſt, bynde all the churche vniuerſally vnto the common receaued latine tranſlacien contrary to the iudgement of all the auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t doctours of the churche: and condemine all godlye and faythfull interpretours of the Bible fowlly of ingratitude.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .iii. Chapiter.</head>
            <p>VVe of the churche of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land refourmed and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned vnder Kyng Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the
<note place="margin">All truthe and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſſe to be ſought in the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</note> .vi. and al other goſpellers churches doo conſtauntly beleue, that all truthe is to be ſought and beleued, and that all godlyneſſe and true ſeruing &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God is moſt pleyntifully co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed in the holy ſacred authentike hoke the Bible, ſo that the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God is perfytlye prepared vnto all good workes, vnto all good partes of offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and al dueties doyng. And on thys
<pb facs="tcp:2045:10"/>wyſe dothe the goſpellers churche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and thynke of the Canonical ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. Wherin it diffreth toto muche from the churche of heretikes, that moſt vniuſtly eyther defame the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures of vncertayntie and imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or els do not receaue ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular bokes therof, or yf they do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue them, yet they corrupt and myn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gle mangle them, and contende with tothe and nayle that all thynges ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye to godlyneſſe and ſaluacion, are not fully conteyned in them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>The, iiii. Chapter.</head>
            <p>ALſo where S. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> 2. <hi>Pe.</hi>
1.</note> Petre pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth in playne wordes, that propherye, that is to ſaye, the declared ſcripture was not brought by the wyl of man, but the holy men of God beyng enforced ſpake as the holye Gooſt taught them, and that therfore the ſcripture (whych is the worde of prophecye) is not of mannes priuate interpretacion: furthermore where Paule accordyng to S. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 10.</note> Petres wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth vs to moderate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie, that is, the office of interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion
<pb facs="tcp:2045:11"/>after the proporcion of faith, and that the interpretours vſe a diſcrete ſobrietie, and abyde wythin the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of fayth, as the Lorde hath beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vnto euery one the meaſure of fayth. The goſpellers churche admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not euery interpretacion of the ſcriptures after euery ones opinion, but that onely whych is fette out of the ſcripture ſelfe, whych is of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God, by whom the ſcripture is inſpired, whych agreeth wyth hym ſelfe in euery thyng, and accordeth wyth the rule of fayth and charitie, wherof we ſhal anone ſpeake more largely. For the ſcripture can not be expounded by any other ſpirite than by the ſelf ſame, by whom it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered and ſet furthe. <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 8.</note> As Thriſt ſaithe in the goſpel: If you haue God to your father, why doo ye not knowe my ſpeche? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> 8.</note> And the apoſtle ſaithe: He that hathe not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite of Chriſte, is none of his. And agayn: what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knoweth the thinges that be of man, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> but the ſpirite of man which is in him: ſo the thinges that be of God, non knoweth but the ſpirite of God. But we haue not receaued the ſpirit of the worlde, but the ſpirit which is of God, that
<pb facs="tcp:2045:11"/>we may know what thynges are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto vs of Chriſt. In dede after ſuche ſorte we affirme, that the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are cleare, whych the heretikes contende to be obſcure, ſo that in thys behalfe we haue no thyng to do wyth them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>The .v. Chapter.</head>
            <p>IN thys caſe we do in no wyſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte nor contemne the diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, reaſons,
<note place="margin">what is be attri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto the fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the inter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pretours of ſcript<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</note> and expoſitions of the holy fathers (I meane the auncient olde byſhopes and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the church) vpon the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, as Ireneus, Origene, Chriſoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, Ambrofe, Ierome, Auſten, and ſuche other lyke, ſo theyr expoſition &amp; iudgementes vary in no poynt from the rules of the Apoſtles. For theyr mynde and wyl was, that theyr wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges ſhould be none otherwyſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of, nor no further fidelitie attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted vnto them. Hereof let S. Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym ſelf tel the tale, wher he wryteth to
<hi>Fortunatianus</hi> in hys thyrde epiſtle in theſe wordes: <hi>Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quorumlibet disputa tiones quamuis catholicorum &amp; laudato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum hominum velut ſcripturas canonicas
<pb facs="tcp:2045:12"/>habere debemus, vt nobis non liceat, ſalua honorificentia, quae illis debetur homini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, aliquid in eorum ſcriptis improbare at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> reſpuere, ſi forte inuenerimus <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aliter ſenſerint qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veritas habet, diuino adiuto rio vel ab alijs intellecta uel à nobis. Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ego ſum in ſcriptis aliorum, tales volo eſse intellectores meorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is, we ought not to repute any mennes reaſons and ſayenges, though they be catholyke and prayſe worthye men, as we ought to do the canonical ſcriptures: as thoughe we myght not (ſauyng the reuerence due vnto thoſe men) improue and reiecte any thyng in theyr wrytynges, yf we chaunce to fynde that they meane o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe than the truthe hathe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be vnderſtanden by the helpe of God of vs or of others. As I am in the wrytynges of other, ſuche wolde I haue to be vnderſtanders of myne. The ſame S. Auſten dothe more lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gely expounde thys hys iudgement in his epiſtle to S. Ierome, &amp; in the <hi>5.</hi> chap. of his.
<hi>11.</hi> boke <hi>Contra Fauſtum,</hi> and in hys. <hi>48.</hi> epiſtle <hi>Ad Vincentium,</hi> and in the. <hi>3.</hi> chap. of hys. <hi>2.</hi> boke, <hi>De Baptiſmo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tra Donatiſtas.</hi> Furthermore he rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoneth vpon generall Counſailles
<pb facs="tcp:2045:12"/>wyth <hi>Maximinus</hi> biſhop of the Arianes in hys. <hi>3.</hi> boke, and among other thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges ſayeth: <hi>Sed nunc non ego Nicenum, nec tu debes Ariminenſe, tan<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> praeiudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turus, proferre conſilium: nec ego huius au thoritate, nec tu illius detineris: ſcriptura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum authoritatibus non quorum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is, ſed vtriſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munibus teſtibus, res cum re, cauſſa cum cauſsa, ratio cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ratione con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certet.</hi> But now ought not I (ſayeth ſ. Auſten) to allege the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſail of Nice, nor thou the counſail of Arimine, as though to haue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vpperha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ther by: but by the autorities of the ſcriptures not by euery mannes owne authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but both ſydes hauyng common witneſſes, let mater pleade wyth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, cauſe wyth cauſe, &amp; reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Here you ſee S. Auſten calleth vs from counſailles, yea euen from the moſte ſacred couunſail of Nice, vnto the autoritie of the ſcriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Panormitanus</hi> therfore (a writour of late dayes) ſemeth not to ſpeake fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nor falſly, wher he ſayeth, <note place="margin">Panormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus.</note> 
               <hi>Plus crede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt vni laico afferentiſcripturas, quam genera li concilio vniuerſalem repreſentanti Eccleſiam, ſi ſcripturas non afferat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is more credence (ſayeth he)
<pb facs="tcp:2045:13"/>to be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to one laye man that brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth furth ſcriptures, than to a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſail, whych repreſenteth the hole vniuerſal churche, yf they bring not furth ſcriptures. Therfore yf the ſayenges or iudgementes of fathers or expoſitions of the ſcriptures varye from the canonical ſcripture &amp; the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le of fayth, ther is no cauſe why any man ſhould laye agaynſt vs, that the fathers were ryght famous learned men, ſingular holy men and men of reuerend antiquitie. For the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and apoſtles of Chriſt were grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter learned, more holy, &amp; of more aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient antiquitie than they. Nother is ther any cauſe why any man ſhould charge vs with the multitude of chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that haue agreed in thys or that meanyng, or in thys or that expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of Chriſtes prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Apoſtles and Patriarkes is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy muche hygher reputacion in ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere religion and godly vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of religion, manifeſtly reuealed vnto vs by the ſcriptures. And yf a man wolde recken vs vp thus many and thus many great realmes and hole countreyes that are of thys iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or that, we wyl cheoke hym wyth the
<pb facs="tcp:2045:13"/>trauailes of one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poore Paule, whych filled all places full wyth the playne ſenſe and ſimple vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of the Goſpel from Ieruſalem and the coaſtes lyeng rounde about vnto Illiricum.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>The .vi. Chaptre.</head>
            <p>NOtwythſtandyng in thys behalfe I maye not ſaye naye, <note place="margin">Of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> but the holy fathers the olde interpretours of ſcriptures do many times make mencion of ſome certayne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable &amp; moſt catholyke meanyng of the ſcriptures. But yet we may not vnderſtande that of theyr owne pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar expoſitions, ſeyng they varye ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry often in theyr interpretacions and diſagree wyth them ſelues, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde not wyth other interpretours of moſt excellent iudgement: yea and wonderous many tymes one repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth an others expoſition. As we nede to ſeke no further examples but of S. Ierome in hys Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentaries vpon the Prophetes. And the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke churche of God hathe alwayes had and hath yet at thys daye, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb facs="tcp:2045:14"/>catholike and aſſured true expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicion of the ſcriptures, grounded of the concordaunce of faithe, and ſet forthe for Chriſtes people to folowe it in all poyntes: wherin al godly men, albeit they diſſent in other ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters, yet they agree in it: as wher we read in ſcripture that God made hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen and earth, that he ſpake vnto the fathers, and that he hathe and dothe ſtil rewarde the good and puniſhe the euil: the catholike vnderſtanding of faithe biddeth vs vnderſtande tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſayenges of the true euer lyuing merciful God, &amp; not of a fearce cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el God that were a maker of euil, as <hi>Cerdon, Mercion,</hi> and <hi>Manicheus</hi> in their fonde fables flirted out the mater. Alſo wher we reade that God wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth al in al thinges: the catholike ſence of faith chargeth vs, that we ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke not God to be the autor of ſynne. For we bring and commytte ſynne (as it were by enheritaunce) euen of our owne original vicious poiſoned nature. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy people (while they lyue in this worlde) are endaungered to ſynne, &amp; are ſaued by the mere mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy &amp; free ꝑdone of God, &amp; not by theyr owne merites. Furthermore where
<pb facs="tcp:2045:14"/>the ſcripture ſpeaketh of God, and cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth hym the Father, the ſonne, &amp; the holy gooſt: the catholyke ſenſe of faith &amp; of the church byddeth vs vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that God is one in ſubſtaunce, &amp; three in perſones. And wher the ſcripture affirmeth Chriſt to be very perfite God &amp; very perfite man: the catholike ſenſe of the church byddeth vs vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande Chriſt to be &amp; abyde in diuerſe natures but not confuſed in them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, &amp; yet in one inſeperable perſone. <hi>Praxeas</hi> and <hi>Sabellius</hi> confounde &amp; iom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the perſones together. <hi>Arius</hi> deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſonne to be very God conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancial wyth the father. Valentinus denyeth the ſonne to be very man of al one ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wyth vs. Neſtorius diſſeuereth hys perſone. Eutyches &amp; Timotheus make the natures of hys Godhead &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>heade al one. But the catholike churche alwayes reteyneth her owne true ryght vnderſtandyng of the ſcripture: whych for all that the holy fathers in theyr written workes &amp; diſputacions againſt hereſies haue declared &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſcriptures.</p>
            <p>For that cauſe the holy fathers haue euer obiected the catholyke mynde of the churche to heritikes,
<pb facs="tcp:2045:15"/>howbeit they dyd ſtrayght wayes con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>firme and declare the ſame by the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptures, and deduced it religiouſly out of the chief principles of our fayth.</p>
            <p>As I ſhal anone ſpeake of theſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters more at large. And thys ſelfe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me catholyke ſenſe &amp; vnderſtandyng of the ſcriptures, the goſpellers chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che kepeth diligently perfite, &amp; ſounde euen at thys daye, as Kyng Edward the .vi. and the churche of Englande dyd in hys tyme.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>The .vii. Chapter.</head>
            <p>THerfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpellers chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che dothe not cal euery one at aue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture (tagge &amp; ragge) to be miniſters of Goddes holy worde, <note place="margin">Miniſters of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers churche.</note> but ſuche men as be furſt exerciced in the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and in the catholyke vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of faythe wyth the churche. For ther be choſen vnto the holy miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the churche, men of ſounde doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and vpryght lyfe, accordyng to the Apoſtles rules. And lyke as ſaynt Paule, whan he ordeyned Timothee to be biſhop, byndeth hym as it were wyth an othe, <note place="margin">2. <hi>Timo.</hi> 5.</note> to preathe the Goſpel
<pb facs="tcp:2045:15"/>ſyncerely, ſayeng: I charge the in the ſyght of God and our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt and of the choſen holy angels, that thou kepe and obſerue thys with out raſheneſſe of iudgement. <note place="margin">2. <hi>Timo.</hi> 4</note> And eft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones he ſayeth: I charge thee before God &amp; our Lorde-Ieſus Chriſt, whych ſhal iudge both the quicke &amp; the deade at hys appearing, and in hys kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, preache the worde, be feruent, and reproue in ſeaſon and out of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. &amp;c. Euen ſo doth the Goſpellers churche bynde theyr miniſters by an othe, that they make no newe gloſes nor expoſicions of theyr owne heades nor vtter in theyr docerine any thing againſt the ſcripture and the true ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike vnderſtandyng of fayth: but euery where and in euery point both to reſpecte &amp; onely folowe the canone and rule of faythe. And in the yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conuocacions which the goſpellers churche vſeth, there is diligent inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicion and ſearche made vpon the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, and vpon the lyfe and doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of euery miniſter, whether it be ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de and vpryght or not, leaſt the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer fal of the miniſter ſhould make a good parte of the churche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to hys ſpiritual charge, to fal miſerably
<pb facs="tcp:2045:16"/>into euil wyth hym.</p>
            <p>The lyke ordre was appointed &amp; ſet furthe by kyng Edwarde the .vi. to hys churche by hys publyke com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, onely the fault of not executyng the ſame was in ſome of hys corrupte doublefaced dreamyng counſailours, and traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous harted Popiſhe Biſhoppes and ordinaries, by whom the vertuous good Kyng was deluded.</p>
            <p>And ſo in thys mater againe we are moſt farre of from the heretikes churche by al meanes. For the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tykes (bothe Papiſtical and Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtical) lyke as they renne whan no man ſendeth them, nor haue any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde to the ſayd general rule, inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as they be a rule and a lawe to them ſelues, euen ſo maye they in no wyſe abyde any reformacion or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the chief prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of our faithe and religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on.</note> In dede the Goſpellers churche dothe moſt religiouſly kepe the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke vnderſtandynge of the churche and the chief principles of the true ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke religion and doctrine. Our congregacion beleueth and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the fyrſt promiſe that the eternal almyghty God hym ſelfe made &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced
<pb facs="tcp:2045:16"/>in Paradiſe, ſayeng: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ge.</hi> 3.</note> I will ſet enemitie betwene the and the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (or that ſpecially appointed wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) and betwene thy ſede and her ſede. It ſhall treade downe thy head, and thou ſhalt tread vpon hys heele. For we knowe &amp; acknowlage that the furſt and principall grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of our faythe and ſaluacion were ſattled and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>priſed in thys promyſe. For we are loſt through our owne ſynne, but we are ſaued by the mere mercie of god through chriſt, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, like as God hathe frely choſen vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euerlaſting, euen ſo he openeth vnto vs by hys worde (wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is beſt tyme in his ſight bothe for his owne glorie and our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie) that we through hys grace ſhould beleue in Chriſt the ſonne of the moſt ſouerayne hyghe God and of that excellent woman, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.</note> the moſt bleſſed virgine Marie, and ſo be ſaued. For Chriſt by hys pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full paſſion hathe broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſtamped vnder fote the head or kingdome of the Deuil, in that he hathe conquered deathe, aboliſhed ſynne, &amp; deſpeched damnacion quyte out of the waye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all faithfull chriſtianes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .8. Chapiter.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:2045:17"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ve and oure Goſpellers churches do beleue and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligiouſly embrace that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and eternal couenaunt that God made to Adam, <note place="margin">The coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aunt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od with
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en.</note> furſt in Paradiſe, &amp; afterwarde ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tymes renewed and playnly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted with the holy fathers, as Noe, and ſingularly wyth Abraham the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther of the beleuers, adding therto the Sacrament of Circumciſion. For the Lorde appeared vnto Abraham, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 17.</note> and ſayd vnto hym: I am <hi>El Saddai,</hi> a myghty ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g God, euery where pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and omniſufficiently fillyng all wyth all good thynges. Walke befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re me and be perfite, and I ſhal rayſe vp, that is, I ſhal repayre my couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t betwene me and thee, and betwene me and thy ſede after thee in theyr ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations with an euerlaſtyng coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt, that I may be thy God &amp; thy ſedes after thee.</p>
            <p>Al theſe ſayenges we applye alſo vnto vs, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ala.</hi> 3.</note> in that the Apoſtle ſayd: yf you be of Chriſt, than in dede ye are the ſede of Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and heyres accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the promiſe: in that Baptiſme was geuen vnto the churche in ſtede of Circumciſion: and alſo in that we
<pb facs="tcp:2045:17"/>haue receaued Ieſus Chriſt our Lord the ende and accompliſhement of all the promyſes.</p>
            <p>Our churches do religiouſly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the moſt holy tables of thys eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nal couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,
<note place="margin">The tables of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenaunt.</note> grauen wyth the very fyngre of our almyghtye ſouerayne Lorde God, in two tables of ſtone with great myſterie, and to thintent they ſhould the longer indure and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the churche of the Iſraelites &amp; of al faythfull beleuers throughout al the hole worlde, of God hym ſelfe by hys moſt bleſſed ſeruaunt Moſes. In the which as it were in a certain ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom ſhort ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me (and yet moſt fully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded) we haue recyted and contey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned al myſtical maters perteynyng to godlyneſſe, and the moſt ſure teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of Goddes good wil towardes vs, and the moſt perfite rule of al out offices and dueties.</p>
            <p>Theſe tables (I ſaye) that were written wyth the fyngre of God, and proclaymed beforehande wyth God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des owne mouth in that great church at the mount Synai, we kepe entier perfite, ſounde &amp; vncorrupte: we take awaye nothyng, we altre nothyng, we putto nothyng, we leaue out no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng,

<pb facs="tcp:2045:18"/>we thruſt in nothyng contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to Chriſtes mynde, we chaunge nothynge at al. From the botome of our hartes therfore we abhorre Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrye, whiche we ſe alſo condemned ſo zelouſly and ſo earneſtly of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes and Apoſtles. And therfore we ſhould thynke it abhominable wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, in caſe ther be ſene in our te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples (dedicated only vnto God) any Images eyther of God hym ſelfe or of hys ſayntes, muche more of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane men or women. S. Paule rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonyng with the moſt wyttye learned Brekes of Athenes, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.</note> ſayeth: For aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as we are the generacion of God, we ought not to iudge that the alwelding God is lyke vnto golde or ſyluer or ſtone craftely grauen, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the inuencion of man. By meanes wherof we reade alſo that S. Iohn the Apoſtle and Euangeliſt charged Chriſtes Churche, ſayeng: Babes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of Images: <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Io.</hi> 5.</note> which wordes the auncient writour Tertullian in hys boke <hi>De corona militis</hi> expoundeth thus.
<hi>Cuſtodite vos ab Idolus: non ia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ab idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria quaſi ab officio, ſed ab idolis; id eſt ab ipſa eorum effige. Indignum enim vt ima go Dei viui, imago idolis &amp; mortui fiat.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2045:18"/>That is, kepe your ſelues from ydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, not now from ydolatrie, as from the ſeruice doyng, but from the ydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, that is, from the very ymages of them. For it were wrong, that the y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the lyuing God ſhould be the ymage of an ydole, and of a deade thyng. Therfore our churches are by theſe wordes acquieted from the cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of hereſie, whych a great meignye of biſhoppes, preachers, and Papiſtes (wyth ſtampyng and ſtaryng, ſcol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and roaryng) charge vs wythal, and for none other cauſe, but that the ymages of God and hys ſayntes be throwen out of all Chriſtes temples, and were in no wyſe receaued any more in Kyng Edwardes dayes, but the ſcriptures of the lyuyng God ſet in their places. Ther is no doubt (ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<hi>Lacta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cius, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Li.</hi> 2. <hi>ca</hi> 19.</note> Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinus</hi> ſcholemaiſter) but ther is no religion, wherſoeuer an ymage is. And S. Auſten in hys Cataloge, wherin he rehearceth al the hereſies of hys tyme, reckoneth amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them, one
<hi>Marcella,</hi> a woman of <hi>Carpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratia,</hi> whych worſhipped the ymages of Ieſus Chriſt, of Paule, of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> and of <hi>Homere,</hi> wyth makyng addraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and incenſing to them. For the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:2045:19"/>martir S. Ireneus in the 24. chap. of hys fyrſt boke <hi>Contra haereſes</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that the heretikes called <hi>Gnoſtici</hi> dyd worſhip the expreſſe lyuely pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ymage of our ſaueour Chriſt, the paterne wherof they ſent vnto Pilate the lieutenaunt of Iewrie who fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the meanes to haue Chriſt, ſet furthe (as an heathen man) by ymage lyke vnto hym ſelfe whan he was alyue, by ſingular connyng payntours and caruers. And yet that biſhop and mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tir inueyed to the vttermoſt of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer agaynſt that ymage, whyche the
<hi>Gnoſtici</hi> ſet ſo muche price by: <note place="margin">A</note> and yf it were now to be had, it ſhould be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among the moſt holy reliques.</p>
            <p>But thys Biſhop was not a ſeuere earneſt perſecutour and enemye of ymages and ymage ſeruice alone: for it is knowen to all men what <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Salamine Cyprus</hi> dyd, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> as he wryteth of him ſelfe in hys gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke Epiſtle, that S. Ierome tranſlated into latine: whych doubtles he wolde not haue done, yf he had thought E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyphanius facte to haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſacrilege.</p>
            <p>Epiphanius alſo ſawe a vaile han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging in a certain churche dore ſtained and paynted, and hauyng an ymage
<pb facs="tcp:2045:19"/>as it hade ben of Chriſt orſom ſaynt. But he plucked it by the ende,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In tomo Hiero.</hi> 3. <hi>fo.</hi> 73. <hi>b</hi>
               </note> and re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it downe thinking it vnworthy that the image of a man ſhould heng in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche of Chriſt, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary (as he ſaithe playnly) to the autoritie of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And he exhorteth Iohn biſhop of Ieruſalem, to charge the elders &amp; miniſters of that place, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they ſhould heng vp no ſuch vailes, whych come againſt the religion of Chriſt. For he ſayd it was more beſemyng the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a biſhop, to ſee that ſuch ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſitie (for ſo he termeth the vſe of i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages in temples) ſhould be taken out of the waye, whych is not worthy of the churche of Chriſt. Now ther is no good grounde for the papiſtes to obiecte vnto vs the ſentences and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of <hi>Gregorie</hi> B. of Rome, <hi>Damaſcene</hi> the greke wrytour (Bardiners great clearke) and of the ſeuenth Synode, whych they call the Synode of Nice, agaynſt theſe ſo cleare and ſo ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cial authorities. For theſe that I haue alleged are of muche more auncien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; certayntie tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyrs be. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore who ſo euer reporteth vs to be he retikes, bycauſe we lacke ymages, let them fyrſt proue the lawe of god he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie,
<pb facs="tcp:2045:20"/>let them prone the teſtimonies &amp; iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the Prophetes and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles hereſie, and let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proue the ſayenges and doynges of Ireneus, Tertullian, Lacta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius, Epiphanius, Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and Ierome to be hereſie, and whan they haue done ſo, let them com and condemne vs of hereſie alſo. And ſo they wyl do one day, whan they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But yf they ſpare them, let them be good to vs alſo, Now wil we returne to our purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Our churche (called the goſpellers churche) dothe religiouſly holde and confeſſe that moſt excellent and moſt true godly belief called <hi>Symbolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> or the apoſtles Crede. <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Crede.</note> Whyche though it be purported in no place of the ſcriptures in the very ſame forme of wordes that we rehearſe it in, yet it is all holly, and euery title of it fette out of the apoſtles writinges. Thys Crede comprehendeth the moſt plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous full forme of belief, ſo that our elders did by it (as a moſt tryed and certain ſure rule) alwayes proue and trye, who were true ryght catholike beleuers, &amp; who were falſe beleuers and heretikes. <note place="margin">Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. is.</note>
            </p>
            <p>S. Cipriane in the expoſicion of thys apoſtles Crede ſaythe, that this
<pb facs="tcp:2045:20"/>greke worde <hi>Simbolum</hi> is a declaracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a collacion or a gatheryng of ſondry maters together into one forme. And for thys cauſe thys ſame declaracion is ſet and compacte together by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the apoſtles doctrine, that therby it myght be knowne, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Chriſt truly according to the rules of the apoſtles. The holy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir Ireneus after the rehearſal of the apoſtles Crede, ſaythe: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Li. con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> haereſes. Ca.</hi> 3.</note> Foraſmuche as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church diſperſed throughout the hole vniuerſal worlde hathe receaued thys confeſſion and Crede, it obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it diligently, as though the hole churche were dwellyng all in one houſe, and preacheth and confeſſeth it after all one conſonaunt ſort, as if al the churche had but one mouthe. For albeit the ſpeches in the worlde be vnlike, yet the vertue and power of the declaring therof, is but all one &amp; the ſelf ſame one. And nother the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage that is in Spayne, nor the ſpeche that is in Fraunce, ne the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages that are in the eaſt cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treyes, ne yet the Egipcians tongue, nor the Lybianes ſpeche, nother the langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that are vſed in the mydle partes of the world: but as the ſunne of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:2045:21"/>makyng is but one and the ſelfe ſame one in all the hole vniuerſall worlde, ſo dothe the light &amp; preaching of the truthe ſhyne euery wher &amp; ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneth all folkes that are willing to com to the knowlage of the truthe. And nother the biſhop of the churche hym ſelf that hath the beſt vtterau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſpeaketh any thyng elles but theſe ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticles, nother doth he that is of ſlende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer vtteraunce, ſpeake any leſſe. For ſeyng ther is but one and the ſelfe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me one faythe, nother dothe he that is hable to vttre it at large, ſpeake any more, nor he that can not vttre the mater ſo plenteouſly, ſpeake any leſſe. Thus muche hath Ireneus. Therfore it is moſt certainly out of peraue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture, that the ful forme of belefe, is moſt fully comprehended in the Apoſtles Crede, and he that conſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely continueth therin to the ende, ſhall doubtles obteyne euerlaſtyng lyfe, as Athanaſius ſayeth: who ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wylbe ſaued, before al thinges it is neceſſary that he hold the catholike faythe, whych fayth except euery one doth kepe holly and vndefyled, wyth out doubt he ſhall peryſhe euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyngly.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2045:21"/>
            <p>Nother dothe Chriſtes churche of the goſpellers cleaue ſuperſticiouſly &amp; frowardly vnto the wordes, neclec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the holy ſenſe &amp; ryght meaning: and therfore it ioyfully receaueth all declaracions and conferences of faith (called in our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſpeche, Credes) whether they be ſet furthe by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fathers or true faithful counſailes, though in mo and more copious wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, yet nothyng varieng in ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces nor conteynyng any contrarye mater. Therfore we receaue and reue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence the Crede of Nice &amp; of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and the ſeconde ſet furth Crede, called <hi>Symbolum Conſtantinopolitanum,</hi> and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good definitions of faythe agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thoſe ſame. And ſo we reproue and reiecte al hereſies, and holde ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed al heretikes condemned by the holy ſcripture eyther in the Counſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les or out of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſailes. And ſo we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne <hi>Symon Magus</hi> wyth al Symo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye, <hi>Baſilides, Valentinus, Marcion, Braxeas, Artemon, Montanus, Nouatus, Sabellius, Appol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linaris, Arius, Eunomius, Macedonius, Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus, Neſtorius, Eutyches, Priſcillianus, Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Pelagius, Heluidius,</hi> the <hi>Monothelites,</hi> and all other of the lyke leuen. So that the churche of goſpellers is not a congre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gacion
<pb facs="tcp:2045:22"/>of heretikes, nor a ſwarme of ſchiſmatikes, as the Papiſtes and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries do wyckedly and falſly lye vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, but a true chriſtian and catholike churche of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>The .x. Chapter.</head>
            <p>THe very cyuile lawe it ſelf doth alſo recken vs among the catholikes. For the Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perours
<hi>Gratianus, Valentinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and <hi>Theodotius</hi> wrytyng to the people of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantinopole geue them thys decreed commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement. We wil that al people whom our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial clemencie hathe the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of, lyue in that religion, whych S Petre the apoſtle ſet furthe to the Romanes, as the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he him ſelf maketh mencion of, beareth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde euen vnto thys daye: the whych it is euident that biſhop Damaſus &amp; Petre biſhop of Alexandria (a man of apoſtolike holyneſſe) did alſo folowe. That is to ſaye, that we ſhould accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the apoſtles diſcipline &amp; doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Goſpel, beleue one God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of the father and the ſonne and the holy goſt vnder like Maieſtie and
<pb facs="tcp:2045:22"/>holy Trinitie. Thoſe that folowe this lawe, we commaunde to take vpon them and embrace the name of chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian catholikes: and the reſt as (wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and madde folkes) we iudge to beare the infamye of hereticall lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng. &amp;c. If any man be ignoraunt what was the faythe that the holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Damaſus and Peter B. of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exandria profeſſed, let hym learne of the eccleſiaſtical hiſtories. They va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried not one tote from the apoſtolike and Nicene Crede. Therfore ſeing we beleue them wyth all our hartes, we are purged cleane from the ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of hereſie, which our aduerſaries goo about wickedly to diſcredite and blemyſhe vs withall.</p>
            <p>But I knowe well inough, they wyl charge vs, that we doo not only not receaue the tradiciones of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, but alſo contemne them and vtterlyreiecte them: and that therfore it is but loſt labour for vs to pretende an vncorrupte ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de faythe, ſpecially forſomuche as the imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the doctrine of the apoſtolike ſcripture is moſt fully perfyted by vnwrytten tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicion by worde of mouthe, &amp; for that cauſe the vnwrytten tradicions to be
<pb facs="tcp:2045:23"/>of equal authoritie wyth the apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke holy ſcriptures. And ſeyng we reiecte the tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, it foloweth that our doctrine and faith is not perfyte.</p>
            <p>Now in aſmuche as our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris the Papiſtes make theſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> toppe and roote of al theyr maters, as they them ſelues reporte in theyr open de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees and bokes: we wyl talke a lytel (as ſorteneſſe of tyme ſhall ſuffre) of the traditions of Apoſtles &amp; Fathers. I fynde thys worde <hi>Tradicion</hi> many tymes in the holy Apoſtles wrytyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.
<note place="margin">Tradici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> For wher the hiſtorie of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel was not wrytten from the begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng of any man, the Apoſtles of Chriſt, as they ſawe wyth theyr eyes, and hearde with theyr eares, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued out of Chriſtes owne mouthe, ſo dyd they declare in dede the wordes and dedes of Chriſt to the congregaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, by tradicion, or lyuely worde of mouthe, but yet not without ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. For loke what they learned &amp; prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched of Chriſt, they confirmed theſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me by the ſcriptures of goddes lawe, of the Pſalmes, and of the prophetes, And at lenght whan God ſawe tyme he admoniſhed hys Apoſtles by the holy Gooſt, that they ſhould enrolle
<pb facs="tcp:2045:23"/>that lynely tradicion partly in to wryl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng them ſelues, and partly ſhoulde cauſe other to wryte vp the reſt. For ſo the Euangeliſt Luke reporteth, that he wyth al diligent forſyght and ſure ſearche of all thynges before hande, wrote a moſte certayne true hiſtorie as they inſtructed hym, whych fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begynnyng had ſene with theyr eyes, and part of them alſo hade ben mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the thynges the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, which they ſpake of. Suche a wytour was Marke alſo. As for Mathewe &amp; Iohn the Apoſtles, they were both ſeers and hearers them ſelues. Nowe for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as the churche of Chriſt hathe theſe ſcriptures at thys daye, it can not be choſen but it hath alſo the full fayth, doctryne or tradicion of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. For the Apoſtles in theyr wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges left out nothyng, that they beleued neceſſarie, and that ſemed to appertayne to the makyng vp of the doctrine fully perfite. I am not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone nor the furſt that auouche thys. For ther were that haue ſpoken the ſame before me, Ireneus and Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, very auncient olde doctours of the churche. For Ireneus in the fyrſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piter of hys. 3. doke <hi>Contra Valentinianos,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2045:24"/>ſayeth: we knewe not how our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion was beſtowed vnto vs by any other men, than thoſe by whome the goſpel came vnto vs: whyche they at that time preached vnto vs, and after ward by the wyl of God they delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto vs in ſcripture, that is, in wrytyng, to be the foundacion &amp; pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of our fayth. Nother can we ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, what they preached, before they had parfyte knowledge.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Papias in Euſebius Caeſarienſis</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl. hiſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i.</hi> 3. <hi>Ca,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lt.</hi>
               </note> Marke (whan he was Petres in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretour) dyd diligently put in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng what ſo euer he kept in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as neceſſitie required. For thys one thyng he thought vpon, that he would leaue out nothyng that he had hearde. The Apoſtles therfore wrote al that was neceſſarie vnto the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of al faythful beleuers: As Iohn the Apoſtle reporteth in the ende of hys goſpel moſt manyfeſtly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he hath done. <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 21.</note> Ieſus dyd many other thynges (ſayeth he) whych are not written in this boke. But theſe are wrytten, that ye may beleue and lyue. Thys ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture therfore is ſufficient to informe our faythe fully, and to attayne euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng lyfe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2045:24"/>
            <p>Therfore we are certainly aſſured that we haue the declaracion or tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, which the apoſtles taught con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng the ſaluacion of faythful be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuers, ſufficiently and fully compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in the ſcriptures. Touchyng thys tradicion the apoſtle Paule ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king mencion in the furſt to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthianes, ſayth, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor,</hi> 11.</note> that he deliuered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnto them whych he receaued of the lorde. Nother ſpeaketh he in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des by and by folowing any thyng, but the ſame that we reade in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel written almoſt worde by worde. In the ſame epiſtle he ſpeaketh alſo of the ſame tradicion, and ſaythe: I deliuered vnto you that whych I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cori.</hi> 13.</note> that chriſt died for our ſynnes according to the ſcriptures, and that he was buried, and that he roſe again the thyrd daye accordyng to the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Again he maketh mencion of his maner of teaching or tradition 2. Theſ. 3. but he openeth in playne flat wordes whych a one it was. And in the .2. of the Theſſaloni .2. he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth efteſones of tradicion: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort brethren (ſayeth he) ſtande and holde faſt the tradicions whych ye ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue receaued, whether it be by worde
<pb facs="tcp:2045:25"/>of mouthe or by epiſtle ſent from vs. Now Paule comprehendeth all hys hole doctrine, whyche he calleth by a general terme, tradicion, in worde ſpoken, and epiſtle writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, By worde, he vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the preachyng of the goſpel whyche he hade preached pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to the Theſſalonians by lyuely worde of mouthe, after ſuch ſorte and reaſon as the other Apoſtles alſo prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched Chriſt vnto other nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which Luke alſo put in wrytyng, and Paule hymſelfe preached to the Romaynes by hys wrytten Epiſtle. For I ſayde that Luke dyd wyth moſt circumſpect diligence put in wrytyng thoſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that he hade learned of the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les touchyng Chriſtes wordes and dedes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> reporteth, that the olde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: vnderſtode theſe wordes of Paule (according to my goſpel) of the goſpel of Luke. And in dede Paule hym ſelfe in the .1. and
15. Chapters to the Romanes, teſtifyeth that he prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the Goſpell to the Romaynes in hys wrytten epiſtle plaine to al mens vnderſtandyng. For in his epiſtles he treateth of the mater more briefly beyng abſent, whyche when he was
<pb facs="tcp:2045:25"/>preſent wyth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had taught more at large, reformyng by his written epiſtles thoſe errours in the churche, whych the falſe Apoſtles had ſowed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, the tyme while he was abſent: and admoniſhed al men of theyr due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and refourmed yf any thyng were diminiſhed. And for aſmuche as ther remayne foure conſonaunt bokes of the Goſpel, and fourtene Epiſtles of Paule (as I wyll not ſpeake of other Apoſtles epiſtles) who could doubt, that the tradicion or doctrine of the Apoſtles is not fully delyuered and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtred vnto vs?</p>
            <p>In the Actes of the Apoſtles we reade that Luke made mencion of the Apoſtles decrees,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act,</hi> 15.16.</note> whyche other men ral tradicions. But it is expreſſed in cleare playne wordes by the wrytten epiſtle that the Apoſtles ſent furthe at theyr conuocacion tyme, what they ment by theyr decrees or tradicions. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 15.</note> For thus they wryte: It ſemeth good to the holy Gooſt &amp; vs, to charge you wyth no more than theſe neceſſary thynges, that is to ſaye, that ye ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteyne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thynges offred to ymages, and from bloud, and from ſtrangled, and from fornicacion.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2045:26"/>
            <p>Surely thys decree (whych is a right Apoſtolike decree in dede) dothe by al meanes contrarye the tradicions fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely called the Apoſtles tradicions, wherwith faythful chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly burthened in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche at this preſent. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true Apoſtles of Chriſt ſaye: It ſemeth good to the holy gooſt and vs, to charge you wyth nomore. Lo, to charge you wyth no more, ſaye they. For Paules aduerſaries, againſt whom the hole conuocacion houſe of the Apoſtles and elders geueth ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Loke So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates in eccle. hiſto. Li.</hi> 15. <hi>ca.</hi> 22.</note> contended that chriſtians muſt nedes be circumciſed, and obſerue the lawe of Moſes. And made the reſt of the Apoſtles autors of that theyr falſe doctrine. As in our tyme alſo many vnder the prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Apoſtles tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicions, do laye heauy burthens vpon free faythful folkes neckes wyth opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and ceremonies. But what is the Apoſtles ſentence of them? We gaue them (ſaye they) no ſuche com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement. They went furth from vs, but they were not ſent of vs. They are diſtourbours of the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacions. Out of the whyche apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſentence Saint, Paule dyd doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les borowe hys wordes, whyche we
<pb facs="tcp:2045:26"/>reade in the begynnyng of hys epiſtle to the Galathians, in thys wyſe:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.</note> I maruaile that ye are ſo ſone turned from Chriſt, whyche called you by grace, vnto an other Goſpell, whych is nothyng els, but that ther be ſome whych trouble you, and intende to peruerte the Goſpel of Chriſt. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe though we oure ſelues or an Angel from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preache any other goſpel vnto you, than that whych we haue preached vnto you, let hym be accurſed. The Apoſtle in repetyng thys ſame ſentence declareth, howe ware chriſten folkes hade nede to be in receauyng ſuche obſeruaunces, as are ſet furthe in the tytle of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles tradicions. For al tradicions are condemned and denounced accurſed, whych burthen and ouercharge chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten mennes lybertie, and what ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thei be that are not agreable with the written goſpel and doctrine of the apoſtle Paule, yea and wyth the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng of the reſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles, whych is al of one ſorte and conſonaunt in euery condicion.</p>
            <p>In the .15. <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of Matthewe ther is alſo mencion made of the tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Elders or Fathers (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2045:27"/>in the fyrſt to the Galathians) whych Chriſt our Lorde hym ſelfe vtterly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth, bycauſe they were not agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the ſcripture &amp; lawe of God: and calleth Eſaye the prophete to wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe wyth hym, whych alſo condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth al ſuche tradicions of man, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng: They worſhip me in vayne, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng doctrines whych are mennes preceptes. Therfore Tradicions, that is, al doctrines and obſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces that are not agreable to the ſcriptures, or procede of a Iewiſhe ſuperſticion, are barred out of Boddes true ſeruice &amp; worſhip, howe gloriouſly ſo euer they be garnyſhed wyth the tytle of aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent fathers. And the Apoſtle hym ſelf wryteth alſo againſt them. Colloſ. 2. Thus muche of the iudgement of ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pture concernyng Tradicions.</p>
            <p>Now as touchyng the fathers, <note place="margin">Note how bolde Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus is to call the Pope and his shaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inges he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes.</note> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may eaſely gather of theyr owne wrytynges, howe ſore heretikes dyd combre the holy fathers vnder the cloake &amp; pretenſe of the Apoſtles Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacions. For Ireneus in the <hi>.2.</hi> chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his <hi>.3.</hi> boke <hi>Contra Valentinianos,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth: whan heretikes be reproued by the ſcriptures, they fal ſtraight wayes to accuſyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures, as though
<pb facs="tcp:2045:27"/>they were not wel, or were not of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie, and that they be ſpoken after diuerſe vnderſtandinges, &amp; that ſuche as knowe not Tradicions, can not fynde the truthe by the ſcriptures. For tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s were not geuen in wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting but by lyuely worde of mouthe. Thus muche ſayeth Ireneus.</p>
            <p>And what do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Papiſtes obiecte elles vnto vs nowe a dayes, when we laye for vs moſt euident cleare ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? They are come to ſuche a wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and ſhameleſneſſe, that they ſticke not to pronounce in theyr open bokes, that the chief fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine of al er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours is to receaue nothing but only that whych is conteyned in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. For they ſaye, ther is an other kynde of doctrine beſydes, whych they cal tradicions, wherin yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be not wel ſkilled, he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nother go vpryght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the ſcriptures, nor haue any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection or certaintie in the onely ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. Whych ſayeng, as it is not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without great reproche of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal truthe, euen ſo they take no hede, but receaue thoſe tradicions alſo at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture wythout weyeng of them, which the holy fathers themſelues ſer out for the Apoſtles tradicions. For I
<pb facs="tcp:2045:28"/>ſee that the tradicions which they ſet furthe, be not of al one kynde. For ther are, whyche they cal the fathers tradicions, but not directly the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles tradicions. Ther are alſo whych they wolde haue to ſeme all together apoſtolike tradicions. And ther is a diuerſitie in theſe alſo. For ther are ſome that be vtterly hiſtorical tradici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that rehearſe what Chriſt, &amp; what Chriſtes Apoſtles haue ſayd or done: of whyche ſorte Euſebius reporteth that Papias rekoned vp many. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl. hiſto i.</hi> 3.
<hi>ca.</hi> 39.</note> And the ſame wrytour clouteth in other maters, as though they had ben tolde hym by lyuely worde of mouthe, and certayn ſtraunge parables and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines of our ſaueour, wyth dyuers flyme flammes beſydes. And concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the tradicion of Iohn the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le touchyng the age of our Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt (whych Ireneus ſpeaketh of) he that ſeeth not it to be a vayne flamme flewe, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contra Walent.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i.</hi> 39.</note> ſeeth nothyng.</p>
            <p>The tradicion of Policarpus, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl. hiſt. li.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi>
28</note> that Iohn ranne awaye from the bayne, wherin Cerinthus the heretike was, leaſt he ſhould fal, agreeth gayly with the ſcripturely doctrine of the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. Let vs therfore in thys kynde of
<pb facs="tcp:2045:28"/>tradicions holde that is to be holden in al pointes, proue al thynges, holde that whych is good.</p>
            <p>Ther are alſo tradicions ſet furthe of rites and opinions, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De peccat. meritis &amp; remiſſ. li.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 20.</note> but yet they are not in al pointes lyke, nother obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued nor receaued of al men S. Typri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ane and S. Auſten reherſe a tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherby the communion was vſed to be miniſtred vnto yong chyldren vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der bothe kyndes, as a neceſſary ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto ſaluacion: but who medleth wyth that tradicion at thys daye?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epiphanius contra Aerium</hi> wryteth it to be a tradicion of the Apoſtles, that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ſhould .vi. dayes before Eaſter eate nothyng but bread and ſalt, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl. hiſt. li. 5. ca.</hi> 24.</note> but Ireneus reporteth that all churches obſerued not that, as Euſebius telleth the tale.</p>
            <p>In an other place it was ſaid, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Damaſeen Ang. dc Bap. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra. Dona. li.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 7. <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. ca.</hi> 42
<hi>li.</hi> 5 <hi>ca.</hi> 23 <hi>&amp; de cura pro mort.</hi>
               </note> that the Apoſtles commaunded the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer to be celebrated after the maner of the Iewes. But Socrates the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie writer in the <hi>.22.</hi> chap. of the <hi>.5.</hi> boke <hi>Eccl. hiſto.</hi> ſpeaketh agaynſt them.</p>
            <p>Epiphanius <hi>Contra Valeſianos,</hi> ſayeth that the wyueles lyfe of miniſters, is a tradicion. In an other place it is read that the Apoſtles co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded by
<pb facs="tcp:2045:29"/>tradicion, that folkes ſhould pray and offre for the deade: whyche onleſſe it be vnderſtande<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thankes gening, who is it, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.</note> that ſeeth not ſuche maner tradicions manifeſtly repugnaunt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the doctrine of the euangeliſtes and apoſtles, and for that cauſe nothing is to be attributed to theſe and ſuch like? Finally I ſee S. Ireneus in ſondry places wonderouſly preache and beate vpon the tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the apoſtles. And that is it that our aduerſaries wraſte and wrythe to all their feyned tryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kettes and tradiciones of the Maſſe, of Images, of Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kery &amp; cloiſter life, &amp; the reſt of ſuch trumpery. Howbeit the holy man Ireneusin theſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal places vnderſtandeth nothyng cl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les by the apoſtles tradicion, than the commune ſenſe and vnderſtandyng of our faythe, and the very apoſtles Crede. I wyll not deſyre to be beleued in thys caſe, if Ireneus hym ſelfe ſaye not the ſame that I haue ſayde. Reade hys
<hi>.1.</hi> boke <hi>Contra valentinianos, Ca. 2. &amp; .3.</hi> and hys <hi>.3.</hi> boke the
<hi>.4.</hi> chap. In bothe places he dothe agreably rehearſe the articles of fayth in ordre one by one, &amp; wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath done, he plainly calleth thys profeſſion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithe, a tradicion.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2045:29"/>
            <p>Of thys tradiction ſpake Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine the myghty Emperour in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles, whyche Euſebius maketh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte of almoſte in the ende of hys <hi>.3.</hi> boke <hi>De vita Conſlantini.</hi> Thus farre ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the goſpellers churches wythout any buſyneſſe embrace the tradicion that I haue now ſpoken of: but as for other tradicions, whether they be A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles or fathers tradicions, they lay them to the rule of Goddes worde, &amp; as they agree or diſagree, they eyther reiecte them or receaue them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to Chriſt our Lordes owne com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement, Math <hi>.15.</hi> and Col <hi>.2.</hi> Wherof I haue already ſpoken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And I pray you, wherin thynke you the goſpellers churche offendeth in thys behalfe? Herein it hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing adoo wyth heretikes, who hade deuiſed to teache falſe opinions vnto ſuche as were to ſymple, vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe of tradicions, and contrarywyſe to teare in pieces, corrupt, yea and to denye and ſtampe vnder fote the true tradicion, that is, the Apoſtles Trede.</p>
            <p>In thys behalfe I coulde dryng furthe a great deale againſt our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, who recken thys predenſe of tradicions of muche force agaynſt
<pb facs="tcp:2045:30"/>the very ſcriptures and the ſimplicitie of tradicion, yea &amp; for the affirmyng or confutyng of any mater what ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be. But I wyl kepe thys in ſtore tyl a better and a further leaſure.</p>
            <p>Hitherto I haue treated as briefly as I could, of the moſt certain and p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyteſt principles of the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith. Wherby I truſt it dothe ſpecially ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the Englyſhe Churche vnder King Edward the .vi. &amp; the reſt of the goſpellers churches haue deuyſed no newe doctrine of fayth, but enibrace &amp; confeſſe the olde faythe wyth all theyr hartes: and that they reiecte no point of ſyncere doctrine, whether it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the ſcriptures, or by tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s conſonau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the ſcriptures: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are moſt farre of from newe fangled felowes, and obſtinate hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>The .xi. Chapter.</head>
            <p>SO the poore goſpellers church beyng confirmed by this true doctrine of the true faythe,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſtificati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</note> lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to be iuſtifyed, that is, to haue full forgeueneſſe of all theyr ſynnes, ryghteouſneſſe &amp; euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng lyfe, of the only free mercye &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:2045:30"/>grace of God by Ieſus Chriſt, that dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and roſe agayne for vs. We beleue that Chriſt wyth al hys gyftes is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued by faythe, and that by faythe Chriſt dwelleth in our hartes. And that fayth is learned by the worde of the Goſpel, is craued &amp; aſked of God by prayers, and geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> frely by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Booſt.</p>
            <p>We attribute not that vnto man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes merites and mannes workes, whych we knowe is due onely vnto fayth, naye, vnto Chriſt our redemer, and to the fre grace of God. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.</note> For Paul ſayeth: By grace are ye ſaued through faythe, and not of your ſelues. It is the gyfte of God, and not of workes, that no man ſhould boaſt. For we are hys handy worke created in Chriſte Ieſu vnto good workes, whych God hath prepared, that we ſhould walke in them. Therfore we knowe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowlage that workes which procede out of a true faythe, by the ſpirite of Chriſt (powred in to our hartes) and done after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule of Goddes worde &amp; chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> charitie, are good workes in dede: and we affirme, that excepte thoſe that be iuſtifyed, practiſe thoſe workes diligentlye, it is but loſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb facs="tcp:2045:31"/>of them to beaſt of theyr faythe, as Petre the Apoſtle teacheth vs and ſayeth: Geue all diligence in youre fayeth, miniſtre vertue, in vertue kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wlage, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iacob.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.</note> in knowlage temperaunce, in temperau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce pacience, in pacience god lyneſſe, in godlyneſſe brotherly kynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in brotherly kindneſſe loue. For yf theſe thynges be amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge you and be pleynteous, they wyll make you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye nother ſhalbe idle, nor vnfrutefull in the knowlage of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt. But he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lacketh theſe thinges is blinde, &amp; gropeth for the waye with hys hande, &amp; hath forgotten, that he was purged from hys olde ſynnes.</p>
            <p>Thys doctrine of grace and meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, of fayth and workes hath no ſmel of hereſie. And ſo it efteſones clearely appeareth that the goſpellers churche is the true churche of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And if they laye to our charge, that our doctrine is iuſtlye condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, bicauſe we conſtauntly affirme, that man is iuſtifyed by only faythe: thys is to anſwer them, that we haue feyned no newe kynde of ſpeakyng in thys behalfe, nother doo we alone affirme, that faythfull beleuers are iuſtifyed by only faythe. For we bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed
<pb facs="tcp:2045:31"/>that maner of ſpeakyng of the very ſcriptures of the apoſtles and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſtes, and of certain doctours of the churche, that are no heretikes but true catholikes. For I haue all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhewed playnly ynough, that we contende not by thys our ſayeng, that faythe is alone, that is to ſaye, vnfruteful, <note place="margin">If righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe come of the lawe, than Chriſt died in vayne.</note> but that faithe is the only cauſe of our ſaluacion. For it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that we are iuſtified not for our owne workes ſake, but frely for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſake, and ſo our ſynnes are not imputed vnto vs, and that iuſtified folke doo the workes of iuſtice, and yet ſeing the faythfull knowe, that they are iuſtified frely, they aſcribe not iuſtificacion vnto workes, albeit they doubt not but God alloweth the workes of faythe. If it wold lyke our aduerſaries to condemne of hereſie, the doctrine of the Euangeliſtes and Apoſtles, with Origene, Chriſoſtome, and Ambroſe, whych ſaye moſt many feſtly that the faythful are iuſtified by only faythe. In dede we had rather be heretikes wyth them, than ryght fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes and catholykes wyth our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>The .xii. Chapter.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:2045:32"/>
            <p>THe ſame poore Goſpellers churche denyeth not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucion to ſuch as haue fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,
<note place="margin">The woun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne are he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aled by Penaunce.</note> but we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re penaunce is a holſome medicine to heale ſynners in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, yf whan they be accuſed by the worde of God, and enlumined wyth the holy Gooſt, they acknowlege and confeſſe theyr faultes and ſynnes to God, and be hartely ſory for theyr of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſes, &amp; truſt to be forgeuen through Chriſtes merites, &amp; then leade a newe lyfe.</p>
            <p>Now it appeareth agayne in thys place, that we ymagine no newe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of penaunce in the churche of God. It is newe fangled ſtuffe that is feyned of ſynnes to be confeſſed (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a man wilbe damned) not only to God, but alſo to hys owne prieſte, by all circumſtaunces euen to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſmal thoughte. It is newe fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de marchaundiſe that is feyned of caſes Papal and epiſcopal reſerued, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act,</hi> 16.</note> of ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faccions and indulgences. Whan the keper of the pryſon at Philippos, fell to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles fete, and beſought them ſayeng: Sirres what muſt I doo that I may be ſaued? they tolde hym. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue
<pb facs="tcp:2045:32"/>in the Lorde Ieſus, &amp; thou ſhalt be ſaued and al thy hole houſe. Saint Petre gaue none other cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſail to the citizines of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi>
2.</note> that were pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in theyr conſciences, &amp; ſayd: what ſhal we doo, you men and brethren? Petre anſwered, Repent and be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed euery one of you in the name of Itſus Chriſt to the remiſſion of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And on this facion we reade that the Apoſtles vſed the keyes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen,
<note place="margin">The Key.</note> whan they receaued them of Chriſt, &amp; after thys ſorte they opened the kyngdome of heauen to faithful beleuers. And on this wyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpellers church vſeth yet ſtil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> key<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt hath geuen them. So that we haue Chriſtes olde keyes, and not the Popes newe monſtrous polling pikepurſe croſſe keyes.</p>
            <p>Lactantius whych was neuer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of errour in treating vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Li.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 20.</note> after that he hade ſayd, ther is no ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion founde but wythin the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like churche, he addeth by and by: But for a ſmuch as heretikes thinke theirs to be alſo the catholike churche: it is to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, that it is the true chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, wherin is religion, confeſſion, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:2045:33"/>penaunce, that holſomly cureth ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ſores, wherunto the fraile fleſhe is ſubiecte.</p>
            <p>Therfore ſeyng thys holſome me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decine is not wanting in the goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers churche, wherin deſperacion is alſo ſingularly beaten downe, &amp; ſure hope faſte fixed and confirmed, who can doubt that the goſpellers churche is the true churche of Chriſt?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>The .xiii. Chapter.</head>
            <p>F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rthermore ther is in oure church brotherly admonicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dmonici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rotherly
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rrection.</note> correction, and ſome reforma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of mennes faultes &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſes. For though all be not yet fully well herein as godly men could wyſhe it, yet ther is ſome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſcipline practiced in the goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers churche.</p>
            <p>Ther is two maner of diſciplines, the one of the clergie, and the other of the laitie. The goſpellers churche by keping of conuocacions and other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient meanes in Germany kepeth the cleargie in ordre to do theyr dutie. And ſo Kyng Edwardes wyl and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement was, to haue hys clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie.
<pb facs="tcp:2045:33"/>as for the diſcipline of the laytie, it confiſteth in good lawes, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent execucion of them. And how that is vſed among the Germanes, let o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men reporte: As for me I knowe nothyng, but heare that it is godlye handled. And though al is not ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite as it ſhould be, &amp; that theyr ſharpe roughe cenſure dothe not thwyte awaye all offenſes at once, yet eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good man knoweth that many thinges are reſerued to be plucked vp by the rootes in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> iudgemet to come: euery godly perſone acknowlageth his fault, and is ſory for it, as often as he dothe leſſe than he perceaueth the Lorde requyreth hym to do. I could demaunde of the Papiſtes, to ſhewe theyr diſcipline whyche they haue in theyr churche: but bycauſe I knowe them as ſhameles as wylde coltes wythout diſcipline, I hade rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende the innocencie of the goſpellers churche, wherof I am an vnworthye membre, than at thys tyme to caſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men in the tethe with theyr faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: I leaue that to the diſcuſſyng of better learned and fyner wytted men than I am.</p>
            <p>Thus farre I truſt the chief mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes
<pb facs="tcp:2045:34"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in the poore goſpellers chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, and therfore we haue nothyng a doo wyth the churches of heretikes &amp; ſchiſmatikes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>The .xiiii. Chaptre.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prayer and inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacion of God by Chriſt.</note> THer is alſo reteyned &amp; kept in the goſpellers churche (as it was in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Kyng Edward) the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſacred and ryght diuine prayer, which Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of God hym ſelfe hath geuen vs, as a handſome ſhorte ſumme of all pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers or formes of prayers, and is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, Matthew. 6.</p>
            <p>Ther is vſed and exerciſed in the Boſpellers churche (and ſo it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vnder King Edwarde) the true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocacion and callyng vpon the true almyghty God, with due thankes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng for the gyftes &amp; benefytes that we haue and do receaue of hym. And that inuocacion we kepe ſyncere and pure. For we vſe our vulgare com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon knowen tongue in all thynges, whether we ſyng, or praye wythout ſyngyng. For who knoweth not
<pb facs="tcp:2045:34"/>that it is free eyther to ſyng or not ſyng in churches, as is requiſite or not requiſite for the congregacions? We call vpon God alone, our moſt mercyfull alknowyng and almyghty father, yea and we call vpon hym, as he hym ſelfe hathe taught vs, by Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde. As for crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, we call vpon none of them, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſtede of the creatour nor wyth the creatour. We call vpon hym, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</note> in whome we beleue: but we beleue in God alone, and not in creatures, therfore we call vpon God and vpon no creature. As for the ſayntes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted (whoſe ſoules lyue wyth God in heauen) we make no prayer to them. For inaſmuche as the ſcripture teacheth vs, that in God alone is all pleyntifull fulneſſe of all good thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and that Chriſt Ieſus dothe at al tymes continually, diligently, fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and moſt perfitely accomplyſhe all the partes of a moſt faythefull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſour wyth God the Father: ther is no cauſe lefte, why faythfull fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ſhould turne vnto others, than vnto God alone, or deſire helpe at any other, than at Ieſus Chriſt, vnto God the Father.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2045:35"/>
            <p>Come to me (ſayeth Chriſt aloude) all ye that labour and are heauy laden, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 11.</note> &amp; I ſhal refreſhe you. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o.</hi>
16.</note> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erely I ſaye vn to you, what ſo euer ye ſhall aſke the father in my name, he ſhall geue it you. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4.</note> And Paule ſayeth: we haue not a hygh prieſt that can not haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on our infirmities, but was tempted in al pointes, lyke as we are, but yet without ſynne. Let vs therfore go boldely vnto the trone of grace, that we may obteyne mercye, &amp; fynde grace to helpe in tyme of nede.</p>
            <p>What offence now doth the goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers churche in thys caſe, whych in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyeng the preceptes recorded in the Euangeliſtes and Apoſtles wrytyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, goeth the ſtrayght hygh waye vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to Chriſt, and deſyreth to be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto God by his only interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? It is not readde in any place of the ſcriptures, that any of the holy Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, whyle they lyued here vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earthe, requyred the interceſſion or helpe of any Patriarke, Prophete, or Martyr. They dyd all cal vpon God by Ieſus Chriſt alone. Why ſhould we than fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe ſtraunge examples? Thys is the true and pure callyng vpon God, this is the true ſeruing of God, and a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb facs="tcp:2045:35"/>to God moſt acceptable, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13. <hi>Ro.</hi>
12.</note> as Paule after the Prophetes beareth playn recorde. Therfore ther is no he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie nor ſchiſme fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in theſe caſes. Saint Auſten in his expoſicion of this place of Iohn, Babes, if any do ſinne, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Super epiſt. Io. canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam.</hi> 1.
<hi>Io.</hi> 2.</note> we haue an aduocate wyth the father Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, ſayeth: Iohn dronke the ſecretes of hydden myſteries out of the Lordes breſt. He (for al he was ſuche a man) ſayd not, you haue an aduocate with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but we haue an aduocate. He ſayd not, you haue, nor you haue Chriſt, but he put in Chriſt &amp; not hym ſelfe: and he ſayd, we haue, &amp; not you haue. He rather put hym ſelfe in the nombre of ſynners, to haue Chriſte hys aduocate, than put hym ſelfe an aduocate in Chriſtes ſtede, &amp; be founde among the proude damned. Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, we haue Ieſus Chriſt the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous an aduocate wyth the father, he is the mercye ſeate of our ſynnes. He that hath holden thys, hathe done no hereſie: he that hath holden thys, hath done no ſchiſme nor ſedicion. Thus ſayeth Auſten. Than ſeyng we folow the commaundement of the Apoſtle, which did nother hereſie nor ſchiſme,
<pb facs="tcp:2045:36"/>and ſeyng we call not vpon Iohn now lyuyng wyth Chriſt in heauen to be our aduocate, but vpon Ieſus Chriſt alone, we may not be iuſtly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led either heretikes or ſchiſmatikes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>The .xv. Capter.</head>
            <p>YEt for all thys the Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers churche contemneth not the ſayntes in heauen,
<note place="margin">Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Saynctes.</note> nor hyndreth them of their due glorie. For we ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them, as the holy ſcripture teacheth vs to honour them. We iudge honourably of them, as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vs to iudge of goddes electe. We thanke God for theyr fayth and doctrine, and we praye that we maye atteyne to theyr company.</p>
            <p>We loue them as brethren, we prayſe them as teachers and examples of faythe, we defende them agaynſt rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and wycked wretches, as fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perſones and worthy of eternall glorye, we acknowlage them as dere frendes and brethrem of the ſonne of God, we preache of them as of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ercel lent inſtrumentes of God, by whome he hathe wrought bothe our ſaluaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and wonderful weyghtye great
<pb facs="tcp:2045:36"/>maters beſydes.</p>
            <p>Now I truſt no man wyll ſaye, that we are enemyes to the ſayntes raignyng wyth Chriſt in heauen, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng we attribute thus muche vnto them of a ſyncere and reuerent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feyned hart, geuyng to God that is Goddes, and to hys ſayntes, that is theirs.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <head>The .xvi. Chapter.</head>
            <p>A Gayn, <note place="margin">Sacram<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Chriſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the cure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the goſpellers chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the hathe no newe Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, nor any mo, than God hym ſelfe hath orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for it. If ther be any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcipline or obſeruaunce, we ſo reuerence &amp; vſe it, as the Lorde hathe commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to vſe it, or as the forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng examples of the Apoſtles haue taught vs.</p>
            <p>Therfore the Churche of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande vnder Kyng Edwarde the .vi. hade not, <note place="margin">Baptiſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and the goſpellers churche elles where at thys daye hathe not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny newe Baptiſme, but the olde Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, euen the ſame that wyth cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng vpon the name of God is geuen in the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the holy Gooſt, to the forgeueneffe of ſynnes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2045:37"/>
            <p>By thys baptiſme we beleue that all are baptiſed to be one body throughe the ſpirite of Chriſt, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 6.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>l.</hi> 3.</note> &amp; that baptiſme dothe alwayes worke effectuallye in faythful beleuers: For Chriſt dothe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes wattre the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of hys bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye wyth hys owne ſpirite.</p>
            <p>So are we therfore the true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres of Chriſtes churche, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e head
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rche.</note> vnder that one head, kyng, ſhepeherde, and moſt myghtye hye prieſt Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde. We are not ſchiſmatical cut of membres. For we ſtycke faſte vnto our one only head Chriſt our Lorde, nother do we fal from the feloweſhip of the membres or body of the church, wherwyth we are knytte together in ſpirite, fayth, and loue: than why are we called ſchiſmatikes? If we dyd put on an other head, or departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the true me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of Chriſt, and were cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled to other ſtraunge membres, and ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtituted a new churche, we might iuſtlye be noted for ſchiſmatikes: but now ſence we acknowlage that ther is but one only churche, and that it is the communion of ſayntes diſperſed throughout al the wyde worlde (in the feloweſhip wherof all our poſſible en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour
<pb facs="tcp:2045:37"/>is to remayne) and ſeyng we crye wyth S. Petre, and ſaye: Lorde,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 6.</note> whyther ſhall we goo? thou haſte the wordes of eternallyfe, and we beleue and haue knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that thou arte Chriſt the ſonne of the lyuyng God: why (I pray you) are we called ſchiſmatikes?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>The .xvii. Chapter.</head>
            <p>VVe do alſo participate and fede of al one ſelf ſame ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Lorde wyth all ſayntes through out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le churche of Chriſt ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring thankes for the vnſpeakeable benefite of our redemption. <note place="margin">The Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</note> We eate al one ſpiritual meate, we drynke all one ſpiritual drinke wyth al faythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les throughout the holy catholyke churche. We are al one breade and one body with Chriſt &amp; wyth al fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulles. By what right therfore are we called ſchiſmatikes? Wyl our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne vs of hereſie, bycauſe we beleue, that to be the beſte forme of celebratyng of the myſtical ſupper, whych Chriſt hym ſelfe hathe inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the Apoſtles delyuered? wyll our aduerſaries condemne vs as he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes,
<pb facs="tcp:2045:38"/>bycauſe we obey Chriſtes bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, <hi>Drynke of thys all,</hi> and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate vnder bothe kyndes? Wyll our aduerſaries condemne vs of hereſie bycauſe we worſhip Chriſt the ſonne of God and of Mary ſyttyng on the fathers ryght hande, and not hidden vnder the kyndes of bread and wyne? wil our aduerſaries condemne vs as heretikes, bycauſe we acknowlage Chriſt to be the only prieſt, and that the one only ſacrifice of hys body on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly once offred vpon the croſſe, is euer of ſufficient &amp; perfyte efficacie in God the fathers ſyght to clenſe the peoples ſynnes: and bycauſe we obſerue the myſtical ſupper for a remembraunce of the ſacrifice, that was offred for vs on the croſſe once for all? Than let them furſt condemne Chriſt hym ſelf, whych inſtituted theſe maters none otherwyſe: let them condemne his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, whyche haue taught vs ſo to beleue and ſo to do. But yf they thinke it wyckedneſſe to thynke any ſuche thyng, than let them ceaſſe to charge the goſpellers church wyth the cryme of hereſie, whych thynketh nothyng herein, whych doth nothyng herein, but as it hathe receaued of Chriſt our
<pb facs="tcp:2045:38"/>Lorde hym ſelfe, and learned of hys holy Apoſtles.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <head>The .xviii. Chaptert</head>
            <p>THe Apoſtle S. Petre ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of wycked teachers, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obedience to Prince. &amp; magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates.</hi> 2. <hi>Pe.</hi> 2.</note> ſayeth: They deſpyſe auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, they are preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſtubborne, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the feare not to rayle vpon them that excelle in honour. &amp;c. we therfore ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horryng that kynde of doctrine, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning that ambicious, ſtubburne, preſumptuous, and raylyng rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe men, doo hartely honour Princes and magiſtrates; and teache all other to doo the like, allegeing S. Petres leſſon: Feare God,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pe.</hi> 2.</note> honour the King. And S. Paules ſayeng: Geue to euery man therfore his duetye, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</note> tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to whom tribute belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth: cuſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to whom cuſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is due: feare, to whom feare belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth: honour, to whom ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour perteyneth. We allowe ſcholes &amp; ſtudie of good ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, &amp; to our power (vn boaſted be it) we doo faithfully &amp; dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly endeauour our ſelues to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them. Further more we doo not damne good &amp; iuſte politicall lawes, nor neceſſary defenſes iuſtly taken in hande, ne iuſte puniſhmentes againſt
<pb facs="tcp:2045:39"/>offenders. We do not improue politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal rule &amp; gouernement, honeſt buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng and ſellyng, good ſciences &amp; law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful occupacions, propretie of goodes and landes, and ſuche lyke, whyche the pretendyng apoſtolical ſectaries the Anabaptiſtes did afore tyme fynd fault wythall.</p>
            <p>We teache folkes alſo to flee ydle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 2.
<hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.</note> and to labour wyth theyr han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, accordyng to the Apoſtles rules: as we are conſtrayned alſo for cauſes of neceſſitie to abandon mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kery and cloiſtre lubbers in our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacions. For the ſolitary lyfe, whyche the olde fathers make mencion of, is an other maner a matter, than thys is, whych at thys daye (where they continue) is a heauye burthenous plage almoſt to al common wealthes. And to recke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp all that can be ſpoken, we haue no thyng adoo wyth eyther ſectes or ſchiſmatikes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="chapter">
            <head>The .xix. Chapter.</head>
            <p>THe Apoſtle S. Paule by the holy ſpirite of God prophe cieth, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of me ates.</hi> 1. <hi>Timo.</hi> 4</note> that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> later tymes ther ſhal come moſt corrupt men, whych ſhall geue hede
<pb facs="tcp:2045:39"/>vnto deceauable ſpirites, and do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of deuilles, for byddyng mariage, and commaundyng to abſteyne from meates, whych God hathe created to receaue wyth thankes geuyng vnto the faythful.</p>
            <p>And ſo we preache ſobre faſtyng, and yet we bryng no meate into an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil name, but alwayes graunt free vſe of meates. Howbeit we teache, that abſtinence is to be kept for a ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, from al meates, what ſo euer we ꝑceaue do make the fleſhe ouer ſtoute, ſo that it obeyeth not vnto the ſpirite.</p>
            <p>As for mariage we forbidde it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to none, eyther ordre or lawfull age, <note place="margin">1.
<hi>Cor.</hi> 7. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.</note> whether it be man or woman: albeit we wype not virginitie from her due prayſe. Mariage is honourable amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g al men, and the mariage bedde vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed. But we deteſte al vncleaneſſe, fornicacion, adulterie, inceſte, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable luſtes. We deteſte dronke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſurfettyng, ryote, and al vntem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraunce. We teache temperaunce, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.</note> ſobre diete, and chaſtitie. We teache wyth the Apoſtle Paule euery one to poſſeſſe hys veſſel in puritie and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wythout the whyth no man ſhal ſee God.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2045:40"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ane charitie is the moſt propre right marke of faihtfull chriſtians, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e &amp; workes of mercie. Ioh.</hi> 13.
<hi>Math.</hi> 25.</note> as our ſaueour ſaithe: In this ſhall all men knowe that you are my diſciples, yf you haue loue one to an other.</p>
            <p>Therfore we condemne malicious manſlaughters, furious bloodſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Kynges and Princes, vniuſt warres, treaſones, murthers, wytch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craftes. &amp;c. For we knowe that mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye and gentilneſſe is more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before God, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oſe.</hi> 6.
<hi>Math.</hi> 9.</note> than all other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. I requyre mercye (ſayeth the Lorde) and not ſacrifice, and the knowlage of God, more than burnt offringes.</p>
            <p>Nowe hereof it commeth, that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng we be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitute in the ſame body that all the holy ſayntes of God are, we ſuffre for thys faythe and for this doctrines ſake, the ſelfe ſame perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cucion, that all that haue confeſſed the ſame faythe that we do, haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred ſence the dayes of Abel vnto this preſent. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh,</hi> 15.</note> If you had ben of the worlde (ſayeth our Lorde in the Goſpell) the worlde wolde loue hys owne. But bycauſe you are not of the worlde, but I haue choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you out of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> worlde,
<pb facs="tcp:2045:40"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>For all though we be ſynners, and doo all amyſſe in many thinges, yet this maye we iuſtly reioyte in, that our aduerſaries hate vs not for ſynnes ſake, but for godlyneſſe and ſyncere profeſſing of Chriſtes reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. For we ſhould haue ben a great deale better taken of many a one, yf we wold fall in to the ſame ryotous loſeneſſe and in to all filthyneſſe of religion and maners that they doo. <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.</note> Therfore we are not ſondred from the felowſhip and communion of the thurche, that hathe ben from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnyng of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worlde vnto this daye. We are ſouldyours with all ſayntes vnder all one Emperour and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn, we haue the ſame hope and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectacion that they haue. We repoſe all the neceſſaries of our life, ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, and helpe, in one only and the ſelf ſame paymaiſter, euen our lorde God Ieſus Chriſt. So we be true membres of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> true churche of Chriſte though our aduerſaries haue hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſynfully accuſed vs (the membres of the goſpellers churche) of hereſye and ſedicyon.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2045:41"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vs vp theyr olde ſong, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uerſaries obiections.</note> that we are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from the holy churche of Rome, that we haue gathered a newe fang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſchiſmaticall churche together, whych hath nother head nor continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of biſhoppes: and therfore that newe fangled churche is no chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, but a conſpiracie of a fewe myſtye raſcal knaues crept out of a ſorte of ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcure felowes and denounced accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed long ago, and ſlaketh and abateth agayne daylye more and more, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraye it ſelfe by that token, ſeyng it is not ſtable, as Bamaliel ſayde, it is of men and not of God.</p>
            <p>Here vnto we make thys anſwere at fewe wordes. Aboue all thynges it is to be weyghed and conſydred, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che a one the true churche of Chriſt is, and wher it is. Not al that are called Iſrael (ſayrth the Apoſtle) are Iſrael: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.</note> euen ſo al that bragge of the name of the churche, be not the true churche: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is the true churche, that is knyt to her one onely huſbande and head Chriſt, that heareth the voyce of none but of her only huſbande and ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde Chriſt, and continueth wyth al ſayntes in hym. From thys maner
<pb facs="tcp:2045:41"/>church we neuer fel, whether it beare the name of the churche of Rome, the churche of Alexandria, the churche of Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinopole or the churche of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioche. For what ſo euer is or euer was of Chriſt, of truthe, and of true godlyneſſe, in theſe or in other chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches throughout the wyde worlde, we embrace it with al our hartes, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour our ſelues to kepe that ſynce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely ſtil vnto the ende. But in dede we are fallen from, and abhorre the Romyſhe wyckedneſſe, the Romyſhe errours, the Romyſhe corrupcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, the Romyſhe lyes, the Romiſhe falſe iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyng knackes, and all abuſes whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſo euer they be, as we vtterly alſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre the Ieweſhip and Mahumetes religion. We do very wel agree wyth the olde ſtates of the churches of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria, Antioche and Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pole, but wyth Mahumetes corrupci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, wherin they ſticke all faſt at thys daye, we agree not. We agree very wel with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde church of Rome, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> choſen veſſel of God S. Paul made ſo muche prayſe of: but we agre neuer a wytte at thys daye wyth the extreme corrupcion of the churche of Rome, whyche theyr owne very
<pb facs="tcp:2045:42"/>frendes can not choſe but ſpeake euil of, bycauſe of the horrible abominaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of it. Are we therfore falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the churche of Chriſt, bycauſe we (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to Chriſtes owne mynde and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement) renounce and caſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye the errours: of the churche of Rome? The holy prophetes of God, the natural ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde, wyth hys choſen Apoſtles, were vndoubtedly in the body of the true and catholike churche of God, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit they had no feloweſhip the while wyth that churche that vaunted them ſelues to be the true churche of God: Naye, that churche excommunicated and perſecuted the Prophetes, and Chriſt and the Apoſtles, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them openly for heretikes and ſchiſmatikes. But yet they were true faythful men and catholikes neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe for al that.</p>
            <p>And how cometh it to paſſe that the goſpellers churche is called a newe fangled churche; which haue theyr re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacion from hence to the begynnyng of the worlde: whych haue Chriſt the eternal ſonne of God to be theyr fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion, and acknowlage the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
<pb facs="tcp:2045:42"/>and Prophetes to be her foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and ſheweth in her ſelfe all the tokens of the true churche in the ſight of all men?</p>
            <p>That is not an headleſſe churche, whych acknowledgeth and reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of God, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, I meane, whom the Apoſtles na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me the heade, and the ſaluacion, the king &amp; chief hygh prieſt of the church.</p>
            <p>Nother is the goſpellers churche without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual ſucceſſion of biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, ſeyng it hathe her relacion euen vnto the Apoſtles of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Chriſt hade the continual rable of biſhoppes and priſtes in the cathedral churche of Ieruſalem euer agaynſt hym. The ſame was agaynſt the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles alſo. But yet who wyll therfore denye, that the Apoſtles churches are the true churches? Who wyl reproue Chriſtes doctrine and hys Apoſtles of lyeng, excepte it be a man to wycked to tel of? Beſydes thys I coulde tell, what a maner one the ſucceſſion of bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes of Rome is, namely of them, that haue made theyr neſte in that Satanicall ſeate for theſe fyue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, yf I wolde do as <hi>Suetonius</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2045:43"/>dyd: and yf I luſted (as he diſcloſed the moſt ſhameful filthy lyues of Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours) to blaſe out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> curſed falſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and abominable wyckedneſſes of many biſhoppes of Rome, and yf I luſted to expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thys ſayeng of Paul: Ther ſhal ſtarte vp from among you, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 20.</note> men ſpeakyng peruerſe thynges, to drawe diſciples after them. &amp;c. But it is ynough to play touche &amp; go in theſe maters, bycauſe I ſpeake to men of vnderſtandyng. That churche is not of a fewe folke, that is diſperſed al the worlde ouer, and comprehendeth all thoſe that be faythfull: except our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries peraduenture meane that whych Chriſt our Lorde ſpake in the Goſpell:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.</note> Many are called, &amp; but fewe choſen. And agayne. Narowe is the gate and ſtrayte is the waye that lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnto lyfe, and fewe ther be that fynde it. Ther is alſo no conſpiracie in vs to any euel purpoſe, but an holy conſent to the doctrine and obedience of Chriſt. As for myſtye knaues we are none, for we caſt no myſtes nor darke clowdes to deceaue any man, but we allure al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the moſt clear lyght of the goſpel.</p>
            <p>Nother is the goſpellers churche
<pb facs="tcp:2045:43"/>buylded vpon obſcure men and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den accurſed, but of Chriſtes owne A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, which were moſt famous no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table men in all the worlde. For albeit the preaching of the goſpel was brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght vnto vs by thoſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, who are of moſt hygh co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the godly, yet we geue not thankes for the begynnyng of ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious a Iewel vnto men, but vnto Chriſt the ſonne of God. Paule was the furſt that preached the Goſpel to the Corinthianes, but for all that he wolde not haue them called Paulini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anes, but he wolde haue them called Chriſtianes. If Chriſt whych is the true lyght of the worlde, yf the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les whych are the lyght bear ours of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, be obſcure men and accurſed, we graunt that our doctrine came of obſcure and accurſed men. But I am ſure, they that go about to bryng them into that ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, ſhal haue light ynough (and to ſpare) in theyr kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, wher hel fyre ſhalbe theyr light.</p>
            <p>They alſo make a moſt open lowd lye, in ſayeng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the goſpellers church of Chriſt abateth and ſlaketh euery daye more and more. Sure they prate that, bycauſe Germanye was ſo late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:2045:44"/>aſſaulted and afflicted wyth war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, &amp; bycauſe of the horrible alteraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. And do not the lyeng wretches ſee, that as Bermanye was tryed as golde is in the fyre, euen ſo is Englande by martires blood? The Lorde ſaid to Petre: Symon, Symon, Satan hathe deſyred to ſifte you, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luce.</hi> 22.</note> as it were wheat, but I haue prayed for thee, that thy faythe fayle not. And whan thou arte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted, ſtreyngthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy brethren. As for Petre he fell, and denyed hys maiſter: yea hys maiſter was alſo hanged on the croſſe, and all hys diſciples ranne awaye. But yet who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gather therof, Ergo Chriſtes doctrine is falſe? Ergo the Apoſtles churche is not the church? Are not our aduerſaries aduiſed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> all which wyll lyue godly, muſt nedes ſuffre perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion? Or why do they not ſee, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they are fayne perforce, with a ſorowfull hart to confeſſe it to be true, that in al theyr hyghe po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pous ruffe, their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is euery daye more &amp; more rent, cut of, &amp; ſlydeth awaye: &amp; that Chriſtes goſpel is clearly preached dayly more and more, and taketh good roote in very Italye and Fraunce, and is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted (for al theyr maſſing myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief
<pb facs="tcp:2045:44"/>and tyrannous tormenting) in wooful England: it putteth furth hys grene buddes in Polone, in Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, in Ilandes not a fewe, yea and in very Turkye alſo. For as faſt as kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Prynces (by the incenſyng of biſhoppes and prieſtes) pſecute faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people with fyre &amp; ſweord, and for al that the wyſe of thys world laye theyr heades together, &amp; take cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſail amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them ſelues, how they may hyndre the kyngdome of Chriſte, and thwyte awaye the preachyng of the goſpel, yet they are neuer the farther for all theyr adoo: the goſpel bloweth hys horne ſtil, &amp; wil do (let the worlde ſtampe and ſtare) euen to the laſt day, til the ſonne of God ſhal come, &amp; geue reſt and glorie to hys afflicted fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, and ſeruauntes, and caſte hys ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes headlong from hys preſence in to the lake of vrymſtone, that ſhall burne for euermore. Now yf a man wyl gather out of al thys ſimple trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe &amp; declaracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the very markes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true ryght catholike church of Chriſt, &amp; wyl wyth aduiſed diligence beholde the goſpellers churche (whom the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes charge wyth hereſie) obſeruing whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more ſure right markes of
<pb facs="tcp:2045:45"/>the true churche maye be founde in the goſpellers churche, he ſhall vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſe, that the goſpellers church is gorgeouſly furniſhed wyth them, and therfore cleare acquieted from all accuſacions and raylyng reportes of al traiterous papiſtes &amp; aduerſaries. For the goſpellers churche receaueth al and ſingular holy ſacred canonical bokes. <note place="margin">The true markes of Chriſtes
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atholike
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hurche.</note> bothe of the olde Teſtament &amp; the newe. To them we geue credence in al pointes wythout contradiccion or doubt, as authencicall, that is, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of them ſelues ful and perfit ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute autoritie. In them we affirme that all truthe is to be beleued, and al myſteries &amp; offices of godlyneſſe are in them fully conteyned and taught: and therfore we referre all the affai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res and buſineſſes of the churche, and al queſtions vnto them, and we geue ſentence, ordayne and refourme after the definitiue iudgementes of them. How be it we receaue not euery man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes iudgement of the holy ſcripture, but the moſt catholike &amp; ryght mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, grounded vpon the mynde of the holy Gooſt, and of the conference of ſcriptures one place to an other, &amp; conformable in all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicions to ſayth
<pb facs="tcp:2045:45"/>and charitie. In thys behalfe we are not vnthankeful but thankful to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitis, and ſet muche price by the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and trauailes that the olde au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fathers beſtowed vpon the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding of the ſcriptures, and we gladly vſe the godly interpretacions of the auncient prelates of the church, whych diffre not from the rule of holy ſcripture. The goſpellers churche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth not the interpretacion of the ſcripture and the charge of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacions to euery man at auenture, but to ſuche as be therto lawfully cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and apointed by the rule of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. We beleue &amp; religiouſly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chief principles of the chriſten fayth, namely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt &amp; health geuing promyſe made of God in Paradiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terning Chriſt our redemer, breaking the head or kyngdome and power of the deuil. We religiouſly embrace that only and eternal couenaunt that God made wyth our fyrſt parentes at the begynnyng of the worlde, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde many tymes renewed it wyth the holy fathers. We religiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleue &amp; obey the moſt holye tables of the couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t written wyth the fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre of God, and conteynyng the hole
<pb facs="tcp:2045:46"/>myſterye of al godlyneſſe. We religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly receaue and vſe the moſte ann<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient articles of belefe, called the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Crede, comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng al the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterye of faythe: whych we fully &amp; ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely beleue wyth al our hartes, and confeſſe it alſo wyth open mouth: and therupon we directly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne all he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſyes &amp; heretical perſons. We ſtycke not alſo to receaue al declaracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and definicions of faythe, whether they be of Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſailes or of Fathers, ſo they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree wyth the Apoſtles Crede. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do we refuſe olde auncient Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicions, yf they agree wyth the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the goſpell, and the apoſtles ſcripture. We preache the grace and merccie of God in Chriſt, we profeſſe, that faithfulle chriſtianes are iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only merite of Chriſt, through only faith in Chriſt, and not by man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes workes or merites. And therwith all we teache that a true faithe can not choſe, but bring furthe good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames.</hi> 2.</note> and we affirme with S. Iames the apoſtle, that a fruteles faithe is a dead faithe. We acknowlage that al men are ſynners, and that all do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſe in verye many thynges, and
<pb facs="tcp:2045:46"/>therfore ſynners haue nede of perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſalue: and we affirme that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce is the healthe geuyng ſalue to them that beleue in Chriſt. And in thys behalfe (as in other caſes) the Keyes of the kyngdome of heauen haue place. Herein we neclecte not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrete admonicion and brotherly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formacion. In al theſe maters we praye continually to God wythout ceaſſyng. We vſe euer the pure cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng vpon God by the interceſſion of Chriſt alone. We receaue and vſe nother mo nor fewer Sacramentes than God hym ſelfe hathe delyuered vnto hys churche. By Baptiſme we haue entraunce into the churche, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough baptiſme we are waſhed and bounden by vowe vnto God. We al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo (the poore churche of goſpellers) are nouriſhed with the myſtical Supper, we celebrate the remembraunce of mannes redempcion purchaced by the bodye broken and blood ſhead of Ieſus Chriſt. We (the goſpellers churche) geue thankes for goddes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, and ſo we openlye profeſſe our faythe. We therfore abyde in the vnitie of the myſticall bodye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one onely heade and Kynge,
<pb facs="tcp:2045:47"/>hygh prieſt &amp; ſhepeherde Ieſus Chriſt: we are not ſondred fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the moſt faſte knytte feloweſhip of the faythful me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres. We thynke honourably of Prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and magiſtrates, that they are the miniſters of God, and therfore they ought to be obeyed and to haue theyr duetie. We co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne nothyng in the political or ciuile ſtates that is not re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pugnaunt wyth godlyneſſe. We for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bydde not meates, whych God hathe made to faythful folkes vſe. We for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bydde not mariage to any ordre or ſtate eyther of man or woman. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicacion wyth al vncleanes &amp; intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraunce we vtterly deteſte. Special<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we commende charitie to be kepte towardes al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. We ſerue God with willyng liberalitie to our power.</p>
            <p>We do paciently beare the croſſe that is layde vpon vs, for the name of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, that aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng conſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the felowſhip of the body of the churche, we maye receaue rewarde wyth al the ſayntes whyche from the begynnyng of the worlde haue ſuffred perſecucion for ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſake. Ther is no newe fang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſtuffe in the goſpellers churche: all is of the olde ſorte, doctrine of Fayth,
<pb facs="tcp:2045:47"/>Belefe, the Keyes, Prayer, the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, and all together. It de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth not fom the head Chriſt: it is not torne from the membres, that is, from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of ſayntes.</p>
            <p>Theſe true markes of the true right tatholike churche of Chriſt, whan thou fyndeſt in the goſpellers church, why doubteſt thou to cal and frely acknowlage it to be the true right catholike churche of Chriſte? Why douteſt thou to forſake al them (as lyers traitours and ſlaunderous railours) that reporte it to be an heri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tical, ſchiſmatical &amp; ſedicious church? I do not nowe (nor in all this hole treatiſe) ſpeake of them, that goo on wyth theyr religion vpon a certayn zeale, and ſpeake euil of vs rather through inſtigacion of other, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theyr owne mynde, beyng not yet ſo fully ſkilled, as to knowe how pure and ſyncere our religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, God ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr hartes: But I ſpeake of thoſe ſpecially, whych are called learned men, and the leaders of the common ſorte, and are not ignoraunt of our doctrine and doynges, and for that cauſe they moſt doggedly and falſely ſlaunder vs: of enuye, hatred, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice
<pb facs="tcp:2045:48"/>againſt the truthe, yea rather of couetouſnes tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ignoraunce, and yet they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make non ende of theyr falſe ſlaunderous railing.</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuche as it is more cleare than the light at none dayes, hauing wyped and dryuen awaye all the myſtye darke clowdes of all our aduerſaryes, that the goſpellers chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is the true right &amp; catholike chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of chriſt, it ſhalbe our partes doubt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les, to contynue conſtauntly in thys true goſpellike churche of God, and to goo on forewarde chearefully in the waye of the lorde, which we haue once allready entred in to. If thys worlde condemne and perſecute vs, we knowe that the lorde hym ſelf in tymes paſt tolde vs before hande of non other, of no pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter, of no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: for the world firſt perſecuted him. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rable of mytred maiſters of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, which vaunt them ſelues to be the general counſail laufully aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to gether in the holy gooſt, doo accurſe vs: let vs conſidre, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord hym ſelfe was condemned before vs of the highe biſhop &amp; college of prieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and elders. Let vs remembre, that our God dothe bleſſe them, that bleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:2045:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>the ſede of Abraham, and dothe curſe them that curſe it: and that we for our true faithe in Chriſt, are the true ſede of Abraham.</p>
            <p>In the meane tyme let vs conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually make our hartye earneſt pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers to GOD our father, by Ieſus Chriſt our lord and ſaueour, without whom we can doo nothyng: that he wold grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs ſtreynght to perſeuer, &amp; conſtauntly to continue in the bleſſed truthe of hys goſpel, &amp; to abyde ſtil in the right ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike churche of Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Truthe hathe the victorie. </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Eſdr. <hi>4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>This is the victorie, that ouercomethe the worlde, euen our faithe. </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Io.
<hi>5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>☞ Emprinted at Vvaterford the .7. daye of Nouembre. 1555. ☞ *</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
